<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Insights</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>http://eoinbrazil.com/</id><updated>2021-08-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>About</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/about-me.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-08-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2021-08-25:/about-me.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m a technology guy with a background in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UX&lt;/span&gt;, computer science and technology commercialisation. I&amp;#8217;ve been with MongoDB for the last six years starting in the Technical Services moving from an engineering role to a team lead role before moving to the Education department&amp;#8217;s Curriculum team producing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m a technology guy with a background in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UX&lt;/span&gt;, computer science and technology commercialisation. I’ve been with MongoDB for the last six years starting in the Technical Services moving from an engineering role to a team lead role before moving to the Education department’s Curriculum team producing and delivering training and content for the MongoDB University. Prior to MongoDB that I spent several years working bringing research to commercialisation and managing consultancy projects with companies in Ireland and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;. Here’s my &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/vitae-eoinbrazil-feb-2019-dev.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; if you want a little more depth about me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love science, technology, craft beer, whisky and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>Keeping your home internet up with an uninterruptible power supply</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/keeping-your-internet-up-with-ups.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-08-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2021-08-24:/keeping-your-internet-up-with-ups.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the age of working from home, work has mostly moved to the laptop for many. This means that the odd blip in terms of power normally on their machine. This isn&amp;#8217;t the case for your home network infrastructure, specifically your router and/or modem. A uninterruptible power supply …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the age of working from home, work has mostly moved to the laptop for many. This means that the odd blip in terms of power normally on their machine. This isn’t the case for your home network infrastructure, specifically your router and/or modem. A uninterruptible power supply (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt;) is essentially a big battery that is used to keep your hardware up when the power is out. Laptops essentially already have a big battery so in many cases a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; is not necessary where the power cuts last for minutes or a couple of hours at most. The recent uncertainty around the winter power supply in the Dublin region prompted me to look more into this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My backup power recipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly routers and modems are pretty low power, they run anywhere from a dozen watts to maybe twice that for the really fully featured models. This means that you can get a moderately powered &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; which will be able to offer power for an hour or more to these devices. I went with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt; and specifically with the &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/products/Back-UPS-Pro-BR-650VA-6-Outlets-AVR-LCD-Interface/P-BR650MI"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR650MI&lt;/span&gt; Back &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; Pro &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;650VA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dublin’s Winter 2022 Power Worries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real worry I had after hearing about the potential problems in Dublin’s power supply this winter (2022) was with brown outs and potentially surges. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19 has limited the maintenace on a number of generators in the national grid and they’re currently undergoing maintence there is an open question as to whether these will be fully functional for this winter, hence the power supply worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A power outage typically doesn’t impact your Internet Service Providers (ISPs) as they’ll normally have their equipment protected with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; and surge protectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Brown outs and surges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surges and brown outs are the two main reasons I went with slightly higher specification model from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt;. Understanding what a surge and a brown out will be helpful to why I chose that specification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brown out is the term for when there is a drop in voltage in the power system. This can be intentional (by the power company) or unintentional (or due to a failure). It’s the intentional brown out scenario with the limited power in Dublin that was the prime reason I got a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt;. I hope this does not happen but if it does, I wanted to be prepared. A brown out can be imposed by the power company in an effort to reduce load and prevent a full power outage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A surge is an abnormally high voltage lasting for a short period of time (millisecond typically), this most often is from lightning strikes. Many &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; offer features to protect against these shocks which can significantly damage sensitive electrical equipment like your router or modem. I’ve already got two &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/ie/en/products/APC-Essential-SurgeArrest-8-outlets-230V-UK/P-PM8-UK"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt; Surge Arrest Essential 8 socket&lt;/a&gt; protectors which I discuss in &lt;a href=""&gt;more depth in this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR650MI&lt;/span&gt; Back &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; Pro &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;650VA&lt;/span&gt; highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of features in this model that helped my choice. You can checkout the &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/products/Back-UPS-Pro-BR-650VA-6-Outlets-AVR-LCD-Interface/P-BR650MI"&gt;full specification on this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It offers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regulation of voltage, it steps up low voltage (brown out) and steps down high voltage (surge) before sending the power to your devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can start cold, so if the power goes completely there isn’t a lag in it providing power to the connected devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;390 Watts / 650 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VA&lt;/span&gt; reasonable sized battery to give around an hour or so of supply to the devices I intend to connect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Setup and installation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few photographs of the unboxing and setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; box and cables&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UPS boxed with cables" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ups-unboxed.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; connected to test battery and first power up&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UPS powered up but with nothing connected" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ups-setup-nothing-connected.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; setup and connected to router and to modem&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UPS setup and running" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ups-setup-router-and-modem-connected.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>Introduction to Modern Databases</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/mongodb-introduction-to-modern-databases.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2021-06-28:/mongodb-introduction-to-modern-databases.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m delighted to announce the public availabilty for a project I created the content for &amp;#8220;Introduction to Modern Databases&amp;#8221;. It is a new free course for educators, instructors, teachers, whether at universities, boot camps, or other learning institutions. It is a free set of materials containing twenty-two lessons in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to announce the public availabilty for a project I created the content for “Introduction to Modern Databases”. It is a new free course for educators, instructors, teachers, whether at universities, boot camps, or other learning institutions. It is a free set of materials containing twenty-two lessons in slide format that can be used partly or fully for teaching needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introducton to Modern Database reflections&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a number of months of work to get our new free course for educators released. I was fortunate to be assisted by &lt;a href="https://www.kenwalger.com/blog/"&gt;Ken Alger&lt;/a&gt; for the technical review and by Bree Grosshandler for the design review. I had thought that my contributions to writing &lt;a href="https://mongodbbook.info/"&gt;“MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd”&lt;/a&gt; was going to be one of my most impactful contributions to the wider MongoDB community but I think the twenty two lessons in this course will likely top this for impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been really privileged that MongoDB has supported my earlier work with the book and most recently with the &lt;a href="https://developer.mongodb.com/article/introduction-to-modern-databases-mongodb-academia/"&gt;“Introductions to Modern Databases” course&lt;/a&gt;. I know the book has made an impact from the feedback I’ve received and I’m really looking forward to hearing and learning from educators about how the course helps them and enables their students in their MongoDB learnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Course highlights for me as I developed it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of highlights in the project for me. I think the most fun one was working with the &lt;a href="https://mws.mongodb.com/?version=latest"&gt;“MongoDB Web Shell”&lt;/a&gt;, indeed I got a number of contributions accepted to get it updated. I hadn’t realized what a helpful tool it is to have a MongoDB shell in your browser. I hope this environment will lower the barrier to adoption of MongoDB as there is now no requirement for any installed software as a requirement beyond that of a web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure to work with a number of academics who were working on their own courses using early versions of this material or who helped us review the material as we developed it. This was really useful validation from the academic side that help hone and nudge the material to the most apprioriate form for eduators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the MongoDB &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTO&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MarkLovesTech"&gt;Mark Porter&lt;/a&gt;, reviewed quite a bit of the course and provide some really solid actionable feedback that helped improve a number of aspects throughtout the course. Mark is a database expert and long-time expert in the field. He delfts added a number of comments that were both unexpected and really helpful. Thanks again Mark!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further information on the course&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mongodb.com/community/forums/t/new-curriculum-content-available-introduction-to-modern-databases/112398"&gt;Announcement post for the course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mongodb.com/article/introduction-to-modern-databases-mongodb-academia/"&gt;In-depth blog post on the course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mongodb.libsyn.com/ep-62-introduction-to-modern-databases-for-educators-with-julianna-chen-and-eoin-brazil"&gt;Podcast interview on the course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mongodb.com/collateral/academia/imdb"&gt;Download page for the course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog/MongoDB"/><category term="mongodb"/><category term="writing"/><category term="teaching"/></entry><entry><title>Krisp Audio Hijacked Loopbacked Zoom Calls</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/krisp-audiohijacked-loopbacked-zoom-calls.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2021-06-23:/krisp-audiohijacked-loopbacked-zoom-calls.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to write up a short post around the audio setup I am using for my day-to-day Zoom Calls. It might be helpful to others and it&amp;#8217;s really given my audio setup a&amp;nbsp;lift. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post covers the specific details that &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;my earlier post didn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/a&gt; as I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to write up a short post around the audio setup I am using for my day-to-day Zoom Calls. It might be helpful to others and it’s really given my audio setup a lift. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post covers the specific details that &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;my earlier post didn’t&lt;/a&gt; as I wanted to expand on my use of &lt;a href="https://krisp.ai/"&gt;Krisp&lt;/a&gt; and how everything is setup for &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt;. These details will allow anyone reading to replicate this configuration for their own conference calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Audio Hardware&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/microphones/podcaster"&gt;Rode Podcaster &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; Broadcast Microphone&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/psa1"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSA1&lt;/span&gt; Studio Boom Arm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/smr"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SMR&lt;/span&gt; Advanced Shock Mount&lt;/a&gt; for my audio hardware for calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Audio Software&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a huge fan of all things &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/"&gt;Rogue Amoeba&lt;/a&gt;, they simply make great software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; I use the advanced audio configuration to enable the original audio input and remove echo cancellation as well as to select a higher quality of audio. These settings are really important as otherwise all the later audio processing won’t really add much quality or value to your audio for other call participants. In most calls, you will still have to manually select use original audio and hopefully down the line that will be might also be a default setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Zoom setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/zoom_advanced_audio_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt;, I use firstly use &lt;a href="https://krisp.ai/"&gt;Krisp&lt;/a&gt; and I pipe my microphone to it as an input. It uses Deep Neural Networks to provide noise cancellation. It has ‘learnt’ many different noises and fairly seamlessly removes these from the audio input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; to further process the audio output from &lt;a href="https://krisp.ai/"&gt;Krisp&lt;/a&gt;. I use the following processing elements: Declick, Dehum, AUHighShelfFilter, AUPeakLimiter, and AUMultiBandCompressor. This is then sent to a ZoomOutputDevice from within the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AudioHijack setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/audio_hijack_zoom_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; processing chain, I’ve added a number of plugins from &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com"&gt;Waves Audio&lt;/a&gt; to further process the audio. Specifically these are: &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com/plugins/deesser"&gt;DeEsser (s)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com/plugins/ns1-noise-suppressor"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NS1&lt;/span&gt; (s)&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com/plugins/vocal-rider"&gt;Vocal Rider Live (s)&lt;/a&gt;. These further clear up any excessive sibilance, general noise, and dynamically control my vocal gain. After some use of this and particularly the vocal gain control, I added an additional processing element (Volume) within &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; to slightly boost the audio post all of the processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I use &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/loopback/"&gt;Loopback&lt;/a&gt; for wiring my Audio Hijack output to &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; and to also link &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/farrago/"&gt;Farrango&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt;. I find that &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/farrago/"&gt;Farrango&lt;/a&gt; is great as a sound board with a few extra sounds from &lt;a href="https://freesound.org/"&gt;FreeSound.org&lt;/a&gt; to add precanned sound effects to any call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Loopback setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/loopback_setup_zoom.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="software"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>Even more updates to my home office</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/even-more-home-office-updates.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2020-10-23:/even-more-home-office-updates.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post follows two earlier posts (&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-updates.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), which describe my furniture and equipment. This post focuses on three very optional pieces of equipment that I have added, an 8-way surge protector, a headphone amplifier, and an upgrade to my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; hub. I also figured I would mention an …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post follows two earlier posts (&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-updates.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), which describe my furniture and equipment. This post focuses on three very optional pieces of equipment that I have added, an 8-way surge protector, a headphone amplifier, and an upgrade to my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; hub. I also figured I would mention an old workhorse that has been plugging away for years at home, my old reliable 4-bay &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Surge protector&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a reliable surge protecctor is something everyone should invest in once you have a decent amount of equipment. It is essentially one of those things you buy and hope you never have to use it, like insurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought two &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/ie/en/products/APC-Essential-SurgeArrest-8-outlets-230V-UK/P-PM8-UK"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt; Surge Arrest Essential 8 socket&lt;/a&gt; protectors. This is a high-end model as it provides a good surge energy rating of 2754 Joules. The surge energy rating is how much energy the protector can absorb before it fails. A rating of 2000 and above is general on the high end of the ratings and aimed at computers with valuable data you want to protect or high value electronics. I use one unit for my home office and I bought a second unit to protect my router, my Unifi Dream Machine, and my home &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;. In the midst of day 2 of a 6 week lockdown, suddenly thinking about business continuity doesn’t seem like that bad a plan!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="APC Surge Arrest Essential 8 socket" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/apc_surge_protector_8way.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Headphone amplifier&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had not really gotten in the audiophile area before and this is my first headphone amplifier. Honestly, I was hesistant to get something but it turns out that there was a new entrant, &lt;a href="https://ifi-audio.com/products/zen-dac/"&gt;iFi Zen &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that was worth considering. I read &lt;a href="https://www.whathifi.com/reviews/ifi-zen-dac"&gt;this review from What Hifi?&lt;/a&gt; that really changed my mind. I took the advice in that review and also got a &lt;a href="https://ifi-audio.com/products/ipower/"&gt;iFi iPower X power supply&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this has greatly improved my listening experience. I haven’t yet upgraded to the likes of Spotify Premium (I’m thinking about it alright!) but even with the freemium version there is a clear improvement with my existing headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="iFi Zen DAC" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ifi_zen_dac.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Thunderbolt 3 Mac Dock&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve added more and more accessories to my home office I was running out of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; ports on my old &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; hub which had 3 ports. I decided to upgrade the capacity and went for the &lt;a href="https://www.caldigit.com/ts3-plus/"&gt;Caldigit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TS3&lt;/span&gt; Plus&lt;/a&gt; which provides a 5 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt;-A ports and 2 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt;-C ports as well as a host of others including an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SD&lt;/span&gt; Card Reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also is powered and has sufficient power to both drive my accessories as well as charging my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a monitor but if I do decide to get one this unit will easily handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Home &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had a Home &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt; for storing various documents, videos, photos and songs. It is a &lt;a href="https://shop.westerndigital.com/products/network-attached-storage/wd-my-cloud-expert-series-ex4100"&gt;Western Digital &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EX4100&lt;/span&gt; 4-bay &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It works well and almost invisibly in the background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>Some updates to my home office</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-updates.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-09-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2020-09-10:/home-office-updates.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I wrote &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;a short piece on my home office setup&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to follow up on that as I&amp;#8217;ve added a few additional pieces of equipment, particularly I&amp;#8217;ve improved my web camera&amp;nbsp;significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Webcam, camera, and stand for&amp;nbsp;mounting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had previously used a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/hd-pro-webcam-c920"&gt;Logitech C920 …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I wrote &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;a short piece on my home office setup&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to follow up on that as I’ve added a few additional pieces of equipment, particularly I’ve improved my web camera significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Webcam, camera, and stand for mounting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had previously used a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/hd-pro-webcam-c920"&gt;Logitech C920 web cam&lt;/a&gt; instead of the Macbook standard webcam and the big change to my setup was adding a &lt;a href="https://fujifilm-x.com/global/products/cameras/x-t200/"&gt;Fujifilm X-T200&lt;/a&gt;. The camera is a mirrorless body and I managed to pick up a deal which included a &lt;a href="https://fujifilm-x.com/global/products/lenses/xc15-45mmf35-56-ois-pz/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUJINON&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XC15&lt;/span&gt;-45mm F3.5-5.6 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OIS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PZ&lt;/span&gt; lense&lt;/a&gt;. The deal and the fact that Fujifilm is one of several camera manufacturers who enabled their cameras to be used as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; web cams with a firmware update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to complete the setup I got a microphone stand, a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/ds1"&gt;Rode &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DS1&lt;/span&gt; Microphone Desk Stand&lt;/a&gt; with a &lt;a href="https://www.camvate.com/camvate-thread-adapter-microphone-stand-5-8quot-27-female-to-1-4quot-20-male-for-camera-monitor_p1361.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAMVATE&lt;/span&gt; 1/4” Male to 5/8” Female Microphone Stand Adapter&lt;/a&gt; to convert the microphone thread to a standard camera thread. The final part to mount the camera was a &lt;a href="https://joby.com/global/ballhead-3k-jb01513-bww/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JOBY&lt;/span&gt; BallHead 3K&lt;/a&gt;, I love Joby’s kit and whilst slightly more expense than other mounting options I’m happy to pay a premium for solid, reliable kit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Charging, Extra Batteries, Lens Hood and Lense filter&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The camera does charge via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; but it’s quite slow to charge (~6 hours). I found a great little charger that both quick and takes two batteries, &lt;a href="https://www.nitecorestore.com/NITECORE-FX1-Charger-for-Fujifilm-Camera-Battery-p/chg-nite-fx1.htm"&gt;Nitecore &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FX1&lt;/span&gt; Fujifilm W126/W126s 2 Hour Dual Slot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There isn’t a way to easily power the camera from mains power whilst it is in use so I also picked up to two additional batteries, a &lt;a href="https://www.hahnel.ie/irish-shop/productUrl/f126twin/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HL&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;F126S&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TWIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PACK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I can easily juggle to my old webcam and swap the battery for meetings so I’m not too worried about this so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to protect the lense, I got a &lt;a href="https://hoyafilter.com/product/pro1d_protector/"&gt;Hoya Pro-1 Digital Protector&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.jjc.cc/index.php/Product/product_info/id/2172"&gt;a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JJC&lt;/span&gt; Lens Hood&lt;/a&gt;. I hope these aren’t needed to protect the lense but if they are I’d much prefer for both of these to take the damage rather than the lense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Chair mounted Green Screen&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally managed to find a green screen that would work with the limited space I had. The &lt;a href="https://www.gig-gear.com/products/cam-a-lot"&gt;Gig Gear Cam-A-Lot Video Conferencing Background Privacy Screen (Green/White)&lt;/a&gt; which simply folds out and sits on the back of your chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A pair of blue light glasses&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit using and abandoning a prior set of blue light glasses as they weren’t a good fit. Second time round, I’d seen a few folks talk about Ambr Eyewear for blue light glasses (here’s looking at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AlanMeaney"&gt;Alan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/patphelan"&gt;Pat&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jesskellynt"&gt;Jess Kelly&lt;/a&gt;) so I went and got a pair of &lt;a href="https://ambreyewear.com/collections/our-range/products/zenith"&gt;Zenith glasses from them&lt;/a&gt;. A week on and I have to admit they do appear to be helping and most importantly they fit well so I’m much more likely to be wearing them for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>My home office and it’s bill of materials</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2020-08-10:/home-office-bill-of-materials.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My home office is literally a desk in the corner of a bedroom which is returned to use as a bedroom after I finish work. All the setup and gear I has to fit this&amp;nbsp;requirement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Furniture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fold away desk isn&amp;#8217;t a typical order but in Dublin there …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My home office is literally a desk in the corner of a bedroom which is returned to use as a bedroom after I finish work. All the setup and gear I has to fit this requirement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Furniture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fold away desk isn’t a typical order but in Dublin there were two companies, &lt;a href="https://ministryofmakers.ie/"&gt;Ministry of Makers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.flyingelephant.ie/"&gt;Flying Elephant&lt;/a&gt; who supply desks that fit the criteria. I went the Halfway desk from Ministry of Makers and even coated it a few times with Danish Oil for good measure. I couldn’t find a fold away chair that I liked nor could I justify buying an Aeron, in the end I went for a &lt;a href="https://www.koplus.eu/en/products/tonique"&gt;Koplus &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TONIQUE&lt;/span&gt; Ergonomic mesh chair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Laptop, mouse and webcam&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My computer is a MacBook and I use it with a &lt;a href="https://griffintechnology.com/products/elevator"&gt;Griffin Elavator stand&lt;/a&gt; as well as a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-roeu/product/wireless-trackball-m570"&gt;Logitech wireless m570 trackball mouse&lt;/a&gt;. I use an &lt;a href="https://www.editorskeys.com/products/vi-vim-keyboard-covers-for-macbook-imac"&gt;EditorsKey Vi cover&lt;/a&gt; on it which probably has saved it from disaster too often to count. I use a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/hd-pro-webcam-c920"&gt;Logitech C920 web cam&lt;/a&gt; instead of the Macbook standard webcam, it’s definitely an improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Networking gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I upgraded my home network during May to a &lt;a href="https://eu.store.ui.com/products/unifi-dream-machine"&gt;Unifi Dream Machine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://eu.store.ui.com/collections/unifi/products/unifi-flexhd"&gt;FlexHD&lt;/a&gt; primarily inspired by &lt;a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/friends-dont-let-friends-use-dodgy-wifi-introducing-ubiquitis-dream-machine-and-flexhd/"&gt;this post from Troy Hunt&lt;/a&gt;. It has been brilliant and I can’t recommend it highly enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Audio gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use two different audio recording configurations, the normal day to day uses a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/microphones/podcaster"&gt;Rode Podcaster &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; Broadcast Microphone&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/psa1"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSA1&lt;/span&gt; Studio Boom Arm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/smr"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SMR&lt;/span&gt; Advanced Shock Mount&lt;/a&gt; for my normal calls (typically Zoom). I use a second setup for recording voice overs which uses a &lt;a href="https://countryman.com/product/e6-earset/"&gt;Countryman E6 Omni &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XLR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (over ear mic) and a &lt;a href="https://www.senalsound.com/product/7950/Senal-XU_1648-XLR_to_USB-Interface"&gt;Senal &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XLR&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XU&lt;/span&gt;-1648&lt;/a&gt;. These are fed through some audio software I’ll cover separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a set of closed &lt;a href="https://www.audio-technica.com/en-us/ath-m40x"&gt;Audio-Technica &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ATH&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;M40X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for my headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lighting gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My lighting is from a &lt;a href="https://www.elgato.com/en/gaming/key-light-air"&gt;Elgato Key Light Air&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="https://lumecube.com/products/video-conference-lighting-kit-for-remote-workers"&gt;LumeCube Video Conference Lighting for Remote Working&lt;/a&gt;. I only recently got the Elgato and it’s replaced LumeCube as my main light. I plan on using the much smaller LubeCube as a secondary light or when traveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Additional gear for various tasks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a &lt;a href="https://www.hootoo.com/p/b07yb2znrn"&gt;HooToo &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; C Hub&lt;/a&gt; to manage all the peripherals. I have a few extras pieces that I use for teaching including a &lt;a href="https://shop.astropad.com/"&gt;Luna Display&lt;/a&gt; (allows me to use an iPad as a second screen and indeed input to my laptop), a pair of &lt;a href="https://joby.com/global/gorillapod-flexible-camera-tripods/"&gt;Joby Gorillapod tripods&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MEKO&lt;/span&gt; Upgraded Fine Tip Stylus Pen for an iPad. I also have a &lt;a href="https://joby.com/global/griptight-pro-2-mount-jb01525-bww/"&gt;Joby GripTight Pro 2&lt;/a&gt; which I use to hold my phone as an ad-hoc whiteboard with the &lt;a href="https://reincubate.com/camo/"&gt;Camo app&lt;/a&gt;. I have also been experimenting with &lt;a href="https://obsproject.com/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OBS&lt;/span&gt; Open Broadcast Software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have a pack of &lt;a href="https://agilestationery.co.uk/products/video-conference-cards"&gt;Video Conference Cards&lt;/a&gt; from Agile Stationery which are great fun to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Software&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href="https://matthewpalmer.net/vanilla/"&gt;Vanilla&lt;/a&gt; to manage the menu bar, &lt;a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/amphetamine/id937984704"&gt;Amphetamine&lt;/a&gt; to keep my laptop on, &lt;a href="https://www.keyboardmaestro.com/main/"&gt;Keyboard Maestro&lt;/a&gt; for various macros, &lt;a href="https://folivora.ai/"&gt;BetterTouchTool&lt;/a&gt; for a nice toolbar, and &lt;a href="https://manytricks.com/witch/"&gt;Witch&lt;/a&gt; for window screen switching. I use &lt;a href="https://www.yellowmug.com/snapndrag/"&gt;SnapNDrag Pro&lt;/a&gt; for screen or window captures. I use &lt;a href="https://www.telestream.net/screenflow/overview.htm"&gt;ScreenFlow&lt;/a&gt; for capturing the voice overs of lessons and indeed any video offline capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of my audio software, I went all in on &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/"&gt;Rogue Amoeba&lt;/a&gt; and love all of their software. I use &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/soundsource/"&gt;SoundSource&lt;/a&gt; for managing my sources, &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; for various tasks including some preprocessing on my mic input, &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/loopback/"&gt;Loopback&lt;/a&gt; for wiring my Audio Hijack output to my Zoom or desired application, and &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/farrago/"&gt;Farrango&lt;/a&gt; for adding the odd random sound effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;SoundSource Setup&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SoundSource setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/soundsource_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Audio Hijack Setup&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AudioHijack setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/audio_hijack_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Loopback Setup&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Loopback setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/loopback_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="software"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>MongoDB The Definitive Guide 3rd Edition Available</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/mongodb-book-available.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2019-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2019-12-13:/mongodb-book-available.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The book is now available as eBook with the paperback version due by the end of the Month. You can also read it directly on &lt;a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920049531.do#"&gt;O&amp;#8217;Reilly&amp;#8217;s Learning Platform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fantastic to see the book and my name on sites like &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/MongoDB-Definitive-Powerful-Scalable-Storage-ebook-dp-B082J7DMBX/dp/B082J7DMBX"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/mongodb-shannon-bradshaw/1125068161"&gt;Barnes &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Noble&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd Edition" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/thumbnail_amazon_listing.png"&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/MongoDB-Definitive-Powerful-Scalable-Storage-ebook-dp-B082J7DMBX/dp/B082J7DMBX"&gt;Amazon&amp;nbsp;Listing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd Edition - Barnes &amp;amp; Noble" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/barnesandnobles_listing.png"&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/mongodb-shannon-bradshaw/1125068161"&gt;Barnes …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The book is now available as eBook with the paperback version due by the end of the Month. You can also read it directly on &lt;a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920049531.do#"&gt;O’Reilly’s Learning Platform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fantastic to see the book and my name on sites like &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/MongoDB-Definitive-Powerful-Scalable-Storage-ebook-dp-B082J7DMBX/dp/B082J7DMBX"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/mongodb-shannon-bradshaw/1125068161"&gt;Barnes &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Noble&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd Edition" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/thumbnail_amazon_listing.png"/&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/MongoDB-Definitive-Powerful-Scalable-Storage-ebook-dp-B082J7DMBX/dp/B082J7DMBX"&gt;Amazon Listing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd Edition - Barnes &amp;amp; Noble" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/barnesandnobles_listing.png"/&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/mongodb-shannon-bradshaw/1125068161"&gt;Barnes &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Noble listing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll be updating the book’s &lt;a href="https://mongodbbook.info/"&gt;website/landing page&lt;/a&gt; with affiliate links once I’ve got them and please consider addingthe book’s Twitter account at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MongodbT"&gt;“MongodbT”&lt;/a&gt; to your Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/MongoDB"/><category term="mongodb"/><category term="writing"/><category term="book"/><category term="website"/></entry><entry><title>Making a landing page for MongoDB The Definitive Guide</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/mongodb-book-landing-page.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2019-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2019-11-30:/mongodb-book-landing-page.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In advance of the book launch later in December I&amp;#8217;ve been doing a little preparation. It turns out that Github is proving not just a useful location for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mongodb-the-definitive-guide-3e/"&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt; but that it also is an excellent place to host the book&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://mongodbbook.info/"&gt;website/landing page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owe …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In advance of the book launch later in December I’ve been doing a little preparation. It turns out that Github is proving not just a useful location for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mongodb-the-definitive-guide-3e/"&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt; but that it also is an excellent place to host the book’s &lt;a href="https://mongodbbook.info/"&gt;website/landing page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owe a lot of thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mhausenblas"&gt;Michael Hausenblas&lt;/a&gt; and his own excellent book on &lt;a href="https://programming-kubernetes.info/"&gt;Programming Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt; which served as the inspiration and guide for my own landing page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This used Github Pages and Jekyll with the &lt;a href="https://github.com/orderedlist/minimal"&gt;‘minimal’ theme&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://github.com/orderedlist"&gt;Steve Smith&lt;/a&gt;. I also choose to use this approach for my landing page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I turned to &lt;a href="https://gandi.net"&gt;gandi.net&lt;/a&gt; for my domain registration and in keeping with several other O’Reilly authors, I chose a &lt;em&gt;.info&lt;/em&gt; domain. I decided on the short, simple, and available &lt;a href="https://mongodbbook.info/"&gt;mongodbbook.info&lt;/a&gt; domain name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After adding the content to the landing page, including a soon to be active Twitter account at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MongodbT"&gt;“MongodbT”&lt;/a&gt;. I made some minor tweaks to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mongodb-the-definitive-guide-3e/mongodbbook.info/blob/master/_config.yml"&gt;_config.yml&lt;/a&gt; file, specifically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;twitter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;eoinbrazil&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"https://mongodbbook.info/"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;plugins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;jekyll-sitemap&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;jekyll-feed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This minor additions allow for attribution to my twitter handle as well as providing a &lt;a href="https://mongodbbook.info/sitemap.xml"&gt;sitemap xml file&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="https://mongodbbook.info/feed.xml"&gt;atom feed file&lt;/a&gt;. The Sitemap file allowed me to submit it to Bing, Google, and Yandex to allow it to be crawled a little sooner than if left to the automated crawler searches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/MongoDB"/><category term="mongodb"/><category term="writing"/><category term="book"/><category term="website"/></entry><entry><title>Co-authoring MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd Edition</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/mongodb-book.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2019-10-31:/mongodb-book.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d been holding off on this post for the last few months as I&amp;#8217;d being asked by Shannon Bradshaw to help write the third edition of &amp;#8220;MongoDB: The Definitive Guide&amp;#8221;. I wanted to wait until it was well underway and by the time I&amp;#8217;d gotten back to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’d been holding off on this post for the last few months as I’d being asked by Shannon Bradshaw to help write the third edition of “MongoDB: The Definitive Guide”. I wanted to wait until it was well underway and by the time I’d gotten back to this post, it ended up being past the first copy writing check of the entire book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd Edition - Powerful and Scalable Data Storage front cover" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/thumbnail_MongoDB-TheDefinitiveGuide-3ed.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The O’Reilly page is at &lt;a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920049531.do"&gt;“MongoDB: The Definitive Guide, 3rd Edition - Powerful and Scalable Data Storage”&lt;/a&gt;. It’s all coming along smoothly for a December release.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/MongoDB"/><category term="mongodb"/><category term="writing"/><category term="book"/></entry><entry><title>Add the three pillars of Observability to your Python App</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/threepillarsofobservability.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2018-11-10:/threepillarsofobservability.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was at PyCon Ireland 2018 this year and lucky to have my talk on Observability&amp;nbsp;accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/dRpiFMd2EOU?list=PLNeBS51Q0m9_EsF_j4UaMQj3x6-abfcDO" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the talk was &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1k3ORfyxYjV56N4j4f_n5B--kWHWE8qQ93WiuGo2Kjos/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;&amp;#8220;Adding the three pillars of Observability to your Python app&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; and was aimed at an intermediate Python audience defining observability, monitoring as well as highlighting various tools …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was at PyCon Ireland 2018 this year and lucky to have my talk on Observability accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" gesture="media" height="360" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/dRpiFMd2EOU?list=PLNeBS51Q0m9_EsF_j4UaMQj3x6-abfcDO" width="640"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of the talk was &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1k3ORfyxYjV56N4j4f_n5B--kWHWE8qQ93WiuGo2Kjos/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;“Adding the three pillars of Observability to your Python app”&lt;/a&gt; and was aimed at an intermediate Python audience defining observability, monitoring as well as highlighting various tools/libraries I found useful in my work in this area. I spoke about many of my own learnings building observability into existing Python applications and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/PyCon2018-AddingTheThreePillarsOfObservabilityToYourPythonApp.pdf"&gt;Pycon 2018 Talk &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="9daaf609dc0548139dff46c8b9ab1c33" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Blog/Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="observability"/><category term="monitoring"/><category term="bottlenecks"/></entry><entry><title>Celery Database Bottlenecks</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/celerydatabasebottlenecks.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2018-03-31:/celerydatabasebottlenecks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had to refactor some code which uses MongoDB and Celery to store results from a scraping process to a MongoDB collection. It involved a number of whack a mole type performance problems due to the distributed nature of the system, and indeed was leading to the &lt;a href="https://linux-mm.org/OOM_Killer"&gt;Linux out …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had to refactor some code which uses MongoDB and Celery to store results from a scraping process to a MongoDB collection. It involved a number of whack a mole type performance problems due to the distributed nature of the system, and indeed was leading to the &lt;a href="https://linux-mm.org/OOM_Killer"&gt;Linux out of memory (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OOM&lt;/span&gt;) killer&lt;/a&gt; being triggered against some of those workers. I wanted to write up some of the approaches I took as they may be helpful to others and indeed maybe there are better ways out there to handle the same situation (so any feedback would be much appreciated!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inspiration for writing this approach in a blog was another &lt;a href="https://www.vinta.com.br/blog/2018/dealing-resource-consuming-tasks-celery/"&gt;blog post on handling memory intensive Celery workers&lt;/a&gt;. This highlighted yet another Celery setting I wasn’t using on &lt;a href="http://docs.celeryproject.org/en/latest/userguide/optimizing.html#prefetch-limits"&gt;prefetch limits&lt;/a&gt; or indeed aware of. The approach from that blog used Celery’s worker prefetch limiting to avoid running out of memory on the workers. The approach below was what I used to avoid running out of memory. It occurs at one step earlier by avoiding sending tasks to the Celery worker from the Python programme distributing the work than throttling the tasks once on the workers. I think either approach may work and I’m glad to have found the blog to both prompt future thinking and my writing of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Limit task submission if Database queue is at or above the maximum threshold&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This function implemented a simple limit and wait logic for the application calling the specific Celery Workers, the example below uses a trivialised example with a single Worker named ‘celery1’. The Celery task inspection function, celery.task.control.inspect(), is queried in the calling Python programme and the running-threads value for the specific worker (which is only used for this one queue) is what determines whether this function will return. If there are too many existing tasks on the worker, the function will sleep until the number of tasks are less than the value set for the variable, message_queue_max.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 6&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 7&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt; 9&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="normal"&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;check_and_backoff_if_db_queue_at_max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;kwargs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;message_queue_max&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ins&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;inspect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;queue_over_max_length_for_worker_1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;all_stats&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;stats&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;all_stats&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;None&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"No Celery Workers have been detected."&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;logger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ne"&gt;RuntimeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;all_stats&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;keys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;startswith&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'celery1'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;all_stats&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;][&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'pool'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'running-threads'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;message_queue_max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;queue_over_max_length_for_worker_1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;queue_over_max_length_for_worker_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;logger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"The DB queue is above &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; pausing for 15 seconds."&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;message_queue_max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;sleep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;kombu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;exceptions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;OperationalError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Failed to connect to Celery Workers or to RabbitMQ at &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;celery_config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;broker_url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;logger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ne"&gt;RuntimeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Setting appropriate task settings for this type of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DB&lt;/span&gt; task&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to better manage this type of task, I set three of Celery’s Task setting. The results are ignored from the task, the task was configured for only acknowledged late rather than using the default of acknowledge on receipt rather than completion of the task (acks_late), and finally the time limits for this task was removed. The task is also configured to make two retry attempts if it fails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;max_retries&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ignore_result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;acks_late&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;soft_time_limit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;None&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Changing the database usage from a upsert to a insert and ignore approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This step actually removed the need for the backoff for my particular usage where a large number of upserts operations (updates for existing documents or if not present then the document(s) are inserted) were the root cause of the Celery Worker having such a long queue. A change to a insert only approach, which was feasible for my application as it only required the document to be present once, provided close on two orders of magnitute improvement to the database operations and significantly reduced the Celery Worker queue as tasks were no longer backing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bulk_result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;MongoClient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;mongo_uri&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DATABASE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;COLLECTION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bulk_write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;array_of_insert_one_operations&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ordered&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Minor discoveries in a useful practical sense but not core to solving my problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the reading and research to address my queue growing too large and triggering the &lt;a href="https://linux-mm.org/OOM_Killer"&gt;Linux out of memory (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OOM&lt;/span&gt;) killer&lt;/a&gt;, I found two useful Celery setting which I had not been aware of. Firstly, you can setup Celery Workers to receive events using the (“-E”) option which allows for restarting worker pools directly through Celery Flower (the Management &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; I use for Celery) when combined with the “worker_pool_restarts” setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second aspect of our internal tooling using a scraper approach, specifically a number of the workers use tasks that are primarily focused on asychronous &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; requests so these use the &lt;a href="http://docs.celeryproject.org/en/latest/userguide/concurrency/eventlet.html"&gt;Eventlet execution pool&lt;/a&gt;. The deployment uses a standard Celery/RabbitMQ configuration. RabbitMQ uses a default setting where 10 concurrent connections are kept open for the broker pool when used with Celery. The setting “broker_pool_limit” allows for this to be raised, in this example below it is set to 100 which is more suitable for this type of Celery Worker/Eventlet execution pool combination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;worker_pool_restarts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;broker_pool_limit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future directions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tooling currently uses &lt;a href="http://docs.celeryproject.org/en/latest/reference/celery.bin.multi.html"&gt;celery.bin.multi&lt;/a&gt; with bash scripting as each node hosts multiple workers, however it is being containerized so I think my next blog will cover moving to &lt;a href="http://supervisord.org/"&gt;supervisord&lt;/a&gt; with a Celery setup of multiple workers per node providing multiple queues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="queues"/><category term="celery"/><category term="bottlenecks"/></entry><entry><title>Two approaches to scale your processing: Task Queues and Workflows</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/queuesandworkflows.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-09-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2017-09-14:/queuesandworkflows.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was very fortunate to present to the main track at PyCon Ireland 2017 on the topic of scaling your&amp;nbsp;processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/OY_hGTwDaSE?list=PLNeBS51Q0m98FAWRHwQLjV1vja2ZdWpCb" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk was entitled &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1W7WvodRej6A3XAPYWOCS6dZam_z5DV2gXhLimKRrGbM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;&amp;#8220;Two approaches to scale your processing: Task Queues and Workflows&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; and was aimed at an intermediate Python audience to introduce them to the Celery and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was very fortunate to present to the main track at PyCon Ireland 2017 on the topic of scaling your processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" gesture="media" height="360" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/OY_hGTwDaSE?list=PLNeBS51Q0m98FAWRHwQLjV1vja2ZdWpCb" width="640"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk was entitled &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1W7WvodRej6A3XAPYWOCS6dZam_z5DV2gXhLimKRrGbM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;“Two approaches to scale your processing: Task Queues and Workflows”&lt;/a&gt; and was aimed at an intermediate Python audience to introduce them to the Celery and Airflow tools for queues and for workflows respectively. It was more mainstream talk than the data science track I’d prevoiusly presented at and I was able to talk about many of my own learnings building tooling with MongoDB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/PyCon2017-TwoApproachesToScaleYourProcessing.pdf"&gt;Pycon 2017 Talk &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="3fa87c9829184c4189d612283a5c9040" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Blog/Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="data science"/><category term="queues"/><category term="celery"/><category term="airflow"/><category term="rabbitmq"/></entry><entry><title>An introduction to Gradient Boosting</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/gradientboostingwithpython.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2016-10-07:/gradientboostingwithpython.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2016, I again had the pleasure of presenting to the annual Python Ireland Conference or PyCon. I gave a talk on &amp;#8220;Gradient Boosting&amp;#8221; which was aimed at introducing this technique in terms of general data science aspects but also the Python libraries that one can ues for&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="600" height="380" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/W7ZgagPAaxI?list=PLNeBS51Q0m98rI6kyTd5_-33ckRgjUEG3" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2016, I again had the pleasure of presenting to the annual Python Ireland Conference or PyCon. I gave a talk on “Gradient Boosting” which was aimed at introducing this technique in terms of general data science aspects but also the Python libraries that one can ues for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" gesture="media" height="380" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/W7ZgagPAaxI?list=PLNeBS51Q0m98rI6kyTd5_-33ckRgjUEG3" width="600"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source and examples for this talk are in a Github repo &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/pycon2016_talk"&gt;PyCon 2016&lt;/a&gt; as well as some setup instructions to replicate my examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/PyCon2015-PythonMongoDBDataPipelines-Keynote.pdf"&gt;Pycon 2016 Talk &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="5f40e5cb272d41b9b38de535d90fb6dc" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Blog/Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="data science"/><category term="gradient boosting"/><category term="scikit-learn"/><category term="xgboost"/></entry><entry><title>Using the Public Cloud to Scale Your Capabilities</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/usethecloudandrtoscale.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2015-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-11-24:/usethecloudandrtoscale.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting to the &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on 24 Nov 2015 on &amp;#8216;Using the Public Cloud to Scale Your Capabilities&amp;#8217;. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-BeyondASingleInstance"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was the third in my series on R and machine learning to the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting to the &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on 24 Nov 2015 on ‘Using the Public Cloud to Scale Your Capabilities’. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-BeyondASingleInstance"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was the third in my series on R and machine learning to the group. It was the final in the series and covered more advanced topics such as how to scale your machine learning using the Public Cloud (in this talk Amazon’s Web Services such as Elastic Computing)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/DublinR - Beyond the Single Instance - Leveraging the Public Cloud for Large Computations.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version of this talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="796a383ad359473fb3d0fc01ad0e8ae2" data-ratio="0.707182320441989" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Blog/R"/><category term="r"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="public cloud"/><category term="rstats"/><category term="big data"/></entry><entry><title>Data Pipelines with Python and MongoDB</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/datapipelineswithpythonandmongodb.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2015-10-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-10-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-10-08:/datapipelineswithpythonandmongodb.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting at PyCon 2015 and also at MongoDB Days &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; 2015 on building data pipelines with Python and&amp;nbsp;MongoDB. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="600" height="380" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Mjbff6oPyhI?list=PLNeBS51Q0m99ud63wiwrPzbp6rwMqYprP" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of my talks source&amp;#8217;s and examples are in Github repos, &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/pycon2015_talk"&gt;PyCon 2015&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/mongodbdays2015_talk"&gt;MongoDB Days &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; 2015&lt;/a&gt;. The PyCon talk was aimed at introducing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting at PyCon 2015 and also at MongoDB Days &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; 2015 on building data pipelines with Python and MongoDB. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" gesture="media" height="380" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Mjbff6oPyhI?list=PLNeBS51Q0m99ud63wiwrPzbp6rwMqYprP" width="600"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of my talks source’s and examples are in Github repos, &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/pycon2015_talk"&gt;PyCon 2015&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/mongodbdays2015_talk"&gt;MongoDB Days &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; 2015&lt;/a&gt;. The PyCon talk was aimed at introducing how you can use Python for building a data pipeline where MongoDB was the source for your data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/PyCon2015-PythonMongoDBDataPipelines-Keynote.pdf"&gt;Pycon 2015 Talk &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/braz/pycon-2015-using-mongodb-and-python-for-data-analysis-p"&gt;MongoDB Days &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; talk&lt;/a&gt; but was aimed at more advanced MongoDB audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="048a946bfac14d409b9bf6ad1efa50e5" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Blog/Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="data pipeline"/><category term="mongodb"/><category term="data science"/><category term="machine learning"/><category term="scikit-learn"/></entry><entry><title>Recapping SRECon EU 2015</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recappart2.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2015-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-06-13:/sreconeu2015recappart2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second part of my notes and thoughts on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recap.html"&gt;first part&lt;/a&gt; covers focuses on the workshops and some of the talks I&amp;nbsp;attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Opening Keynote - PostOps: Recovery from&amp;nbsp;Operations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tone of the conference was set by Todd Underwood who is the Director …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second part of my notes and thoughts on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recap.html"&gt;first part&lt;/a&gt; covers focuses on the workshops and some of the talks I attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Opening Keynote - PostOps: Recovery from Operations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tone of the conference was set by Todd Underwood who is the Director of Google’s Site Reliability Engineering team. He neatly laid out and introduced &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SRE&lt;/span&gt; as the systems and software engineers who solve production problems with software. The concepts are inspired some what from Adrian Cockcroft’s “NoOps” where there is no operations organisation and it is software developers supported by automation who are working directly with production. This isn’t to say you shouldn’t take the best of operations culture and apply it to your production engineering team. Site reliability engineering needs to be taken as a first-class responsibility / citizen. The talk was a good summary of the various concerns and history as to why the computing sector needs to move beyond the definitions of “Administration” and of “Operations”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Prometheus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://prometheus.io/"&gt;Prometheus&lt;/a&gt; is a new monitoring system built by a number of engineers from SoundCloud and several former Google SREs. This &lt;a href="https://developers.soundcloud.com/blog/prometheus-monitoring-at-soundcloud"&gt;Soundcloud Developers post introduces&lt;/a&gt; the system and how it has been designed to overcome issues they found with StatsD and Graphite. The four key features they highlighted during the talk where:
1. A multi-dimensional data model which allows pretty manuipulation of dimensions of the data
2. Simplicity to install and operate
3. Scalable data collection and decentralized architecture (time series collection via a pull model over &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;)
4. A query language&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has a number of very useful features building on the work for systems like &lt;a href="http://opentsdb.net/"&gt;OpenTSDB&lt;/a&gt; and it has pretty much the same data model and syntax as OpenTSDB. This is where time series is identified by a metric name and a set of key-value pairs. These can be queried by its expression browser and the data can be visualised on dashboard using their PromDash tool. It hooks into to the likes of PagerDuty and supports a Nagios plugin allowing Prometheus to ‘bridge’ to existing Nagios deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big change is that Prometheus requires you to instrument your own code directly. The rationale for this is that is will provide higher quality service based monitoring.n instrumentation is usually worth the price. There are a range of client libraries for most programming languages. These client libraries allow metrics to be exposed via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; using either the protocol buffers format or as a simpler text-based format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Prometheus servers scrape metrics from the instrumented applications directly or using a gateway. These samples then stored locally with rules executed over this data to generate new timeseries or to generate alerts. These streams of timestamped values all belong to the same metric with the same labeled dimesions. Timestamps are at a resolution of a millisecond resolution and the values are saved as 64-bit floats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a range of blogs about it but I’d highly recommend my fellow programme committee member Brian Brazil’s series monitoring on the &lt;a href="http://www.boxever.com/tag/monitoring"&gt;Boxever blog&lt;/a&gt;. He was key team player in helping to organising the conference and is a committer to Prometheus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Signatures, Patterns, and Trends: Timeseries Data Mining at Etsy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can well imagine one of the maxims at Etsy being, if it moves, measure it and even if it doesn’t, measure it. They record a ton of metrics and now have over a million metrics. This means they’re literally drowning in data and traditional approaches means that both alerting and graphicing are not cutting it. Graphs don’t scale well to a million distinct metrics and alert thresholds become very prone to triggering due to false positives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to manage this magnitude of metrics they have developed the &lt;a href="https://codeascraft.com/2013/06/11/introducing-kale/"&gt;Kale stack&lt;/a&gt;. It consists of &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/skyline"&gt;Skyline&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/oculus"&gt;Oculus&lt;/a&gt;, the first help detects anomalous metrics and the latter is used to correlate patterns between metrics. This stack helps them detect any issues and make better hyptotheses around their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I definitely like the ‘hack’ with the shape description alphabet for a timeseries similarity. The Etsy stack is focused on their problem of lots of metrics and how to monitor the million+ interdependent time-series. It stores these time series in Redis and uses ElasticSearch for the search component. The next iteration of the stack, ‘Thyme’, was the latter end of the talk and looks pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Upgrade Your Database without Losing Your Data, Your Perf, or Your Mind&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charity Majors as ever gave an excellent talk that helped open the minds of many to the dangers of database upgrades. There is a shorter and earlier version of &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/charity/upgrading-databases-without-losing-your-data-your-perf-or-your-mind"&gt;this online&lt;/a&gt;. I have to say go &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/majors"&gt;watch the video&lt;/a&gt; as it is one of the best talks but I’m a bit biased towards this topic these days!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It discusses the apprioriate levels of paranoia you should have, the need to balance effort against risk, and how to capture and replay production traffic to feed this the database. She talked a little bit about their &lt;a href="https://github.com/ParsePlatform/flashback"&gt;flashback tool for replaying MongoDB workloads&lt;/a&gt;. There is a more detailed blog on the Parse site covering &lt;a href="http://blog.parse.com/learn/engineering/mongodb-rocksdb-benchmark-setup-compression/"&gt;how to setup this tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Going Off the Rails: Infrastructure Outage Planning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a nice talk reviewing some of the aspects of a major incident in the London Underground with hardware upgrades, hardware failure and insufficent planning all contributing. It particularly highlighted how the failure to implement one element of the plan around managing the loading/offloading of trains meant chaos and massive queues for passengers. There was a nice section on lesson learnt and plans to prevent future incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk summarised this &lt;a href="https://www.networkrail.co.uk/review-into-disruption-affecting-kings-cross-and-paddington-services-27-December-2014.pdf"&gt;report from Network Rail on the incident&lt;/a&gt; and focused on what learnings SREs could take from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Bad Machinery— Managing Interrupts Under Load&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the Google Storage SREs gave a very interesting talk on the personal side of how we (as individuals) manage interruptions in complex and busy production situations. In the case of SREs who both write code and work oncall it is important to really value keeping the engineering in the flow doing one thing well. It echos an earlier Velocity 2014 talk from Etsy who spoke about “&lt;a href="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/watch?v=FLqucVb_et0"&gt;Mean Time to Sleep: Quantifying the On-Call Experience&lt;/a&gt;” which has &lt;a href="https://codeascraft.com/2014/06/19/opsweekly-measuring-on-call-experience-with-alert-classification/"&gt;a blog post&lt;/a&gt; and their &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/opsweekly"&gt;opsweekly tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These talks are very valuable as understanding and measuring the interrupts can help in crafting better contextualised alerts or in not alerting the engineer unless it is necessary. As more companies deployer larger systems and services these practices will become more wide spread but in the meanwhile it’s great to see how others are managing this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Aside regarding hiring and managing SREs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest ;login Usenix magazine (June 2015, Vol. 40, No. 3) has two great articles including one from Todd Underwood (opening keynote speaker). These are well worth a read to help understand the role and how to hire the calibre of people needed for this type of role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/publications/login/june15/hiring-site-reliability-engineers"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Hiring Site Reliability Engineers” by Chris Jones, Todd Underwood, and Shyjala Nukala&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/publications/login/june15/hixson"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;The Systems Engineering Side of Site Reliability Engineering” by David Hixson and Betsy Beyer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog/SRE"/><category term="sre"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="usenix"/><category term="review"/></entry><entry><title>Recapping SRECon EU 2015</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recap.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2015-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-06-07:/sreconeu2015recap.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of helping to organise as well as attending &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. I have pulled together a few of my notes and links of interest to recap what was an excellent conference. It was focused on operations engineering and on site reliability topics with speakers from many …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of helping to organise as well as attending &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. I have pulled together a few of my notes and links of interest to recap what was an excellent conference. It was focused on operations engineering and on site reliability topics with speakers from many of the big names (e.g. Google, Facebook, Yelp, Spotify amongst others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal goals outside of my programme committee role for the conference where to find out what counterparts where doing in similar or larger organisations. My current role with MongoDB involves a lot of customer facing work and troubleshooting so I was very interested in the Postmortem and Large Scale Abstract Design workshops. I’ve presented a lot of work to the Dublin R Usergroup on machine learning so I took the opportunity to attend a similar session from Splunk. I dipped in and out of the other sessions at the conference. In the reminder of this blog post, I’ll firstly cover my notes from the three workshops then move to my notes from the various talks and finally add some useful tools / pointers from other attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, the last topic and most scary talk was on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; data protection, specifically the view / thinking of the European Court of Justice (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECJ&lt;/span&gt;) and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; Safe Harbour agreements. It was given by Simon McGarr, a well known Irish socilitor who’s been a great advocate of Digital Rights in Ireland. It painted a scary picture that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; may end with two distinct Internets before 2015 is finished once the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECJ&lt;/span&gt; makes a ruling (expected in Oct/Nov). I’m not a legal expert so instead I’ll refer you to a &lt;a href="http://eulawanalysis.blogspot.ie/2015/03/does-facebook-and-usa-violate-eu-data.html"&gt;recent summary&lt;/a&gt; by Simon himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Workshops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Postmortems&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I can safely say this session changed my thinking around Postmortems. I cannot recommend the work of Etsy and John Allspaw highly enough in this regard. He was fantastic and brought us on a journey of understanding helping us to evolve a more nuanced and mature sense of investigation as well providing links to a larger toolkit to facilitate such sessions. I think these two bullet points encapsulate John’s teaching
 * “Key goal of postmortems is to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEARN&lt;/span&gt; rather than bring list of TODOs away”
 * “Goal of workshop on Postmortems is to help you ask better questions not give a magic process”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to facilitate their Postmortem process Etsy have developed their own tool &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/morgue/blob/master/README.md"&gt;Morgue&lt;/a&gt; that allows them to tag, annotation and extract/link to specific issues in their Jira ticketing system. There’s a great talk by &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/devopsdays/morgue-helping-better-understand-events-by-building-a-post-mortem-tool-bethany-macri"&gt;Bethany Macri on the Morgue tool&lt;/a&gt; that explains it in more depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reference for improving communications that John mentioned in his talk is the book “Crucial Conversations” and having recently bought a copy, I’d also concur. I also got a pointer to another excellent post from Lara Hogan (also at Etsy) on &lt;a href="http://larahogan.me/blog/giving-presentation-feedback/"&gt;giving presentation feedback&lt;/a&gt;. Etsy really impressed me at SRECon and looking forward to more of their talks in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work and thinking are influenced on the five steps (see below) based on Dekker’s methodology. As such it very useful to read &lt;a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.411.4985&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf"&gt;“Reconstructing human contributions to accidents- the new view on error and performance” by Sidney &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W.A.&lt;/span&gt; Dekker&lt;/a&gt; to help understand this “new thinking” and the rationale behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five steps for a postmortem create a concept-depentant account from the context-specific event data:
1. outline the sequence of events in context-specific language
2. if necessary, break the sequence of events into episodes, if necessary (avoiding the global singular timeline)
3. determine how the world changed during each episode
4. identify what the focus of attention, the goals of people and what knowledge was active at that point in time
5. work up to a conceptual description&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thinking and John’s talk put forward the view that Reductionism is false that outcomes can be foreseen in complex systems, that time is reversible (you can’t rewind the buffer to reconstruct), and likewise that complete knowledge is not attainable. It underlined that “Why” is a terrible question to ask and immediately translated to “Who is responsible”. In a postmortem, when you ask “How” it translate to “What is responsbile”. Once you ask “Why” you lose context and it means that at least half of the key context and details are lost. One of the worst methods for a postmortem is the “Five Whys” as not only does it lose context but it also further loses complexity as it linear sequential. It is much better to ask “Why else” and better again to ask “How”. A key point was that “Why” is often used as a technique to shutdown conversations. At this point, there was recommendation to read the book “Crucial Conversations: Tools for Talking When Stakes Are High” and it’s definitely well worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so much useful stuff that John covered that a full blog series could be dedicated to it and my recommendation is that you view one of his many videos online if you’re interested in learning more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Large Scale Abstract Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great half day small team classroom event where a real-world large scale engineering problem was presented. Each team had to come up with as much of the following as time allowed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A high-level design that scales horizontally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial SLIs, SLOs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimates for hardware required to run each component&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If time permits, monitoring design and disaster testing scenarios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a great exercise and I’ll refain from saying too much more as we where asked to avoiding sharing the content as they will reuse it. However I can provide a few links to relevant talks/slides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//people/jeff/stanford-295-talk.pdf"&gt;Software Engineering Advice from building Large Scale Systems by Jeff Dean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.somethingsimilar.com/2013/01/14/notes-on-distributed-systems-for-young-bloods/"&gt;Notes on Distributed Systems for Young Bloods by Jeff Hodges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/sites/default/files/conference/protected-files/srecon15europe_slides_nolan.pdf"&gt;Distributed Consensus Algorithms for Extreme Reliability by Laura Nolan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Machine Learning on Machine Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a great series on statistical and machine learning talks, I attended the latter but I’ll include links to both for those who might want to refresh their statisticial skills:
1. &lt;a href="https://github.com/HeinrichHartmann/StatisticsTutorial"&gt;Statistics Tutorial for SREs by Heinrich Hartmann&lt;/a&gt;
2. &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1JsanuUB8_6ae2mWEWyCzxhgcoe68G8EzaDgrgKUOopA/edit#slide=id.g9bd6a2176_2_87"&gt;Machine Learning for Machine Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The machine learning workshop was fast paced and required Splunk so if you’re interested in following the slides you’ll need to install it first. I learnt a few new tricks and enjoyed somebody else giving a talk on that topic (I’ve done a similar talk but with R recently). It was particularly nice to see how to structure the introduction and Splunk is a very powerful tool that I’ll definitely be learning/using more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was so many excellent talks that I can’t list them all. The standards where high and presentations excellent. I’ll include a few that cover the spectrum of topics covered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Operational Software Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theo Schlossnagle gave an excellent talk on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/schlossnagle"&gt;Operational Software Design&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/postwait/operational-software-design"&gt;full slides online&lt;/a&gt;. It covered many tools such as DTrace, &lt;a href="http://backtrace.io/"&gt;backtrace.io&lt;/a&gt;, and their own &lt;a href="https://github.com/circonus-labs/fq"&gt;fq&lt;/a&gt;. He wrote fq to replace RabbitMq due to a number of issues where it was unable to work for their monitoring needs. fq is a brokered message queue using a publish subscribe model. It has been designed for performance and large number of connected clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia’s Yandex (2nd search engine in Russia) talks about the types of load tests that they use and presented 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/yandex/yandex-tank"&gt;Yandex Tank&lt;/a&gt; their tool for this. The &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/sites/default/files/conference/protected-files/srecon15europe_slides_lavrenuke.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/lavrenuke"&gt;abstract&lt;/a&gt; covered the full depth of this talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m tied as which was my best talk as to whether it was from Susan Coghlan on improving infrastructure performance using root cause analysis (+2.5x &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MTTF&lt;/span&gt;) or Avleen Vig on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/vig"&gt;remote working&lt;/a&gt;. Susan’s talk was from the Argonne &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HPC&lt;/span&gt; National Lab and showed how over the last five years, their process has contributed to improved reliability (e.g. 5x improvement &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MTTI&lt;/span&gt;), utilization (10% increase), and changed the problem priortisation approach. I think Avleen Vig wins out on how Etsy manages the challenges faced by engineers, management, and organizations, and ways to address the issues to successfully build distributed teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Useful Tools/Links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of tools and links I got from the talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Nagios related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/nagios-herald"&gt;nagios-herald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://nagios.sourceforge.net/docs/3_0/largeinstalltweaks.html"&gt;Use the use_large_installation_tweaks configuration option in Nagios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Zookeeper related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/twitter/zktraffic"&gt;zktraffic, iptraf / top monitor for ZooKeeper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Kafka related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/edenhill/kafkacat"&gt;Kafkacat, a generic command line non-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JVM&lt;/span&gt; Apache Kafka producer and consumer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Parsely/pykafka"&gt;PyKafka is a cluster-aware Kafka protocol client for python&lt;/a&gt;. It includes python implementations of Kafka producers and consumers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/jamiealquiza/sangrenel"&gt;Apache Kafka load testing weapon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/stealthly/gauntlet"&gt;Apache Kafka Test Framework for Producer and Consumers for Compatibility Testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/stealthly/go_kafka_client"&gt;Go library for Kafka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog/SRE"/><category term="sre"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="usenix"/><category term="review"/></entry><entry><title>My Previous Research</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/my-research.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2015-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-03-22:/my-research.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a hectic few months learning the ins and outs of MongoDB. I&amp;#8217;ve learnt a lot but a request has made me realise that I&amp;#8217;d forgotten to bring a few artefacts from my past along with me and that the Internet has forgotten them as well …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a hectic few months learning the ins and outs of MongoDB. I’ve learnt a lot but a request has made me realise that I’d forgotten to bring a few artefacts from my past along with me and that the Internet has forgotten them as well. Over the years the links to my various disserations and theses have fallen out of circulation due to replacement of webservers and general spring cleaning of former researcher group members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m posting them back to this website with my apologies to those who in the research community couldn’t access them, I honestly hadn’t realised they were not still being hosted on the various servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Investigation of multiple visualisation techniques and dynamic queries in conjunction with direct sonification to support the browsing of audio resources&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Masters thesis investigated sound / music collection management from the view point of browsing coupled with multiple visualisations and filtering. The question asked sought to discover if supporting a different form of navigating these resources might enhance the serendipity of the experience. Looking at it today, it is still an open question as whilst Spotify and similar streaming music services provide a search inspired navigation approach, there is still no ‘browse’ inspired approach that allows you to be lost in oceans of sound, and yet made those serendipitous discoveries. Spotify’s Discover Weekly and Your Daily Mix are one attempt based on similarity metrics but it still lacks the engagement of the user and those moments of self discovery (i.e. when in a physical record store finding that random gem)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/msc_thesis.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Investigating Methods for the Selection and Evaluation of Everyday Sounds for Use As Auditory Icons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PhD thesis investigated everyday sounds, specifically how people categorised these sounds and what meanings they associated with them. My work gathered a range of existing techniques from interaction design and from other domains to elict the multiple meanings that people assoicate with these sounds. The thesis provided a framework and guidance on how to map these meanings to usable categories. My eventual and still unreached goal was to design auditory interfaces using these sounds for public spaces where the sounds would have a communal meaning and a hidden/deeper personal meaning. The very essence of private communication with non-speech sounds in public environments where hidden messages could be passed to the listener due to the deeper understanding of how they would perceive the multiple layers of meaning inherent in the sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/phd_thesis.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A Generic Approach for Data Management combining Financial Modeling with Road Mapping&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PGDip dissertation in technology commercialisation investigated how road mapping could be combined with financial modeling and looked at this in the context of data management. It provided an approach for businesses that allowes for the development of a technology strategy with clearly outlined cost benefits to the business. Road maps, particular technology road maps are a common tool in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; product management mid to long term strategies, however these do not include any clear financial modeling that allows tangible estimates to be developed and matched to the road map. I had worked with a number of companies in the cloud and high-performance computing space during this period and felt the cloud hype (which unfortunately still exists today) needed better tools for senior &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; managers to both understand and justify their technology strategy choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/pgdip_dissertation.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>Machine Learning of Machines with R</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/machinemlwithr.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2015-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-03-21:/machinemlwithr.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following my introduction presentation to the &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on machine learning, I again had the pleasure of being invited to talk on more machine learning. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-machine"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was more intermediate than my &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-treesandforests/"&gt;previous introductory talk&lt;/a&gt;. It used two …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following my introduction presentation to the &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on machine learning, I again had the pleasure of being invited to talk on more machine learning. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-machine"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was more intermediate than my &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-treesandforests/"&gt;previous introductory talk&lt;/a&gt;. It used two datasets focusing on computing cluster job usage statistics (e.g. similar to data from a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HPC&lt;/span&gt; job scheduler) and machine level application and host usage statistics (e.g. similar to those from host monitoring software such as Nagios).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/DublinR - Machine Learning - Machine Learnings on Machines.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version of this talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The techniques covered included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Background on large scale clusters (e.g. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HPC&lt;/span&gt;) and rationale for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; of machine/cluster operational metrics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow for model building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addressing feature selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model assessment and selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a confusion matrix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ROC&lt;/span&gt; plot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approaches to handling prediction errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boosting and Bagging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data set 1 - Job scheduling data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data set 2 - Machine metrics data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary / recap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Unused) A review of various &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; techniques:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision trees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Random forests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;k Nearest Neighbors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support vector machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk focused on the two datasets as well as highlightly how the business context was important to consider when developing the models. The talk looking at using machine learning to improvie the utilisation and scheduling of large scale clusters (significant hardware resources). It recapped some earlier material and focused a little more on feature selection and feature generation as well as applied domain expertise from the data set. It provides two datasets showing examples of how to use R to select, assess and create the models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talk slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="8afe1177b3be4840980b2f252a428b81" data-ratio="0.707182320441989" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Blog/R"/><category term="r"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="machine learning"/><category term="rstats"/></entry><entry><title>Handy Interaction Design - DEFUSE Dublin 2013</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/handyinteractiondesign.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2013-11-11:/handyinteractiondesign.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate to have been asked to present at &lt;a href="http://www.ixd.ie/"&gt;IxDA Dublin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.defuse.ixd.ie/"&gt;Design for Use 2013 (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEFUSE&lt;/span&gt;) conference&lt;/a&gt; on interaction design. I&amp;#8217;ll briefly walk through my talk in this post as technical issues on the night left it a little disjointed. I&amp;#8217;ve included references used in the talk …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate to have been asked to present at &lt;a href="http://www.ixd.ie/"&gt;IxDA Dublin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.defuse.ixd.ie/"&gt;Design for Use 2013 (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEFUSE&lt;/span&gt;) conference&lt;/a&gt; on interaction design. I’ll briefly walk through my talk in this post as technical issues on the night left it a little disjointed. I’ve included references used in the talk for those interested in diving a little deeper into the topics I covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk was aimed at introducing persuasive design as one approach to dealing with the growth of mobile applications and beyond, particularly the increasing ubiquity of devices as illustrated by the Internet of Things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 1 - 3: Our senses and humans as multimodal creatures&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="2" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;‘&lt;/span&gt;Cortex’ man illustrates the amount of wiring in our brain that is dedicated to specific modalities. It highlights that we are multimodal creatures. In the past I’ve worked on a range of alternative interfaces including buttons that you can hear but cannot see. In a world of increasing ubiquity of technology we need to re-imagine how we interact technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IEEE&lt;/span&gt; Multimedia 2005, &lt;a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=1423932"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HCI&lt;/span&gt; Design and Interactive Sonification for Fingers and Ear&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 4 - 7: From desktop to motes and the growth of mobile apps to the Internet of Things&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="4" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jumping to the thoughts of Scott Jenson and the realisation that we simply cannot create an interface or application for every piece of technology as we move from the desktop, to dedicated devices, to motes or invisible technology. The growth of the Internet of Things will drown in us in a cacophony of machine voice, all of which are seeking our most limited resource that of our attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://mobile.smashingmagazine.com/2013/10/08/responsive-website-design-with-ress/"&gt;Responsive design with server side components&lt;/a&gt; and multi-device design all attempt a technological solution focusing on presentation or hardware issues. These are only part of the problem, interaction requires much more than just a technical solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devices such as &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/glass/start/what-it-does/"&gt;Google’s Glass&lt;/a&gt; or wearable ambient displays such as the &lt;a href="http://jorgeandesther.com/lume/"&gt;Lume&lt;/a&gt; show how we are only scratching the surface of what these devices can tell us about their usage, location and context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog entry by Scott Jenson - August 1, 2012 &lt;a href="http://designmind.frogdesign.com/blog/of-bears-bats-and-bees-making-sense-of-the-internet-of-things.html"&gt;Of Bears, Bats, and Bees: Making Sense of the Internet of Things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 8 - 10: Emerging scenarios and contexts of use, device awareness of environment and responsive design/multi-device design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="8" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies are showing us how people are using devices to tackle in a variety of ways that we are only beginning to design for and understand. Google’s study on &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/think/research-studies/the-new-multi-screen-world-study.html"&gt;multi-device use for a variety of scenarios&lt;/a&gt; highlights how we need to re-consider interactions not just in terms of devices but also with regard to the relatedness of the activity and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developments on the technology side such as environmental awareness via Device APIs that allow devices to provide more information about their context of use can help and provide guidance on whether it is appropriate  to interact with the person. Testing and querying what a device can do will still be part of a solution but we also need to focus on behaviors, mental models and the abilities of people in designing new interactions for ubiquitous technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google August 2012, &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/think/research-studies/the-new-multi-screen-world-study.html"&gt;Research Study - The New Multi-Screen World Study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Wright, February 12 - 2013, A List Apart, &lt;a href="http://alistapart.com/article/environmental-design-with-the-device-api"&gt;“Environmental Design with the Device &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 11: A cavet, the difficulties of understanding and eliciting views of how people perceive the world&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="11" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding and eliciting the views and contexts of how people perceive the world is &lt;bold&gt;difficult&lt;/bold&gt; and in this talk I only touch on a few approaches but there are many more that can help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 12: - Moving beyond the traditional interface paradigms&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="12" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to move beyond the command line and graphical user interface paradigms and really start to explore new paradigms such as the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_user_interface"&gt;natural user interfaces&lt;/a&gt; with the likes of &lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/surface/en-ie"&gt;Microsoft’s Surface&lt;/a&gt; and other tangible interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 13 - 18: Using models and approaches such as persuasive design to deal with attention and the clamouring noise from machines, services and applications competiting for attention&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="13" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In tandem, we need to better model people’s behaviors using the likes of &lt;a href="http://www.behaviormodel.org"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BJ&lt;/span&gt; Fogg’s model&lt;/a&gt; which captures motivation, ability, and triggers. It looks at not just a single interaction but right up to changing or habituating behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this type of approach work ? Mike Krieger is a former student of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BJ&lt;/span&gt; Fogg and co-founded Instagram. He uses &lt;a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/anthonykosner/2012/12/01/instagram-will-monetize-for-facebook-by-testing-solutions-one-week-at-a-time/"&gt;these approaches&lt;/a&gt; to decide what the new features will be included in Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fogg has another paper on &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-540-68504-3_3"&gt;‘Mass Interpersonal Persuasion: An Early View of a New Phenomenon’&lt;/a&gt; which looks at Facebook and the psychology of persuasion. It isn’t exactly about creating a viral adoption model but it is a way of understanding how to reach and influence millions of people using this type of technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other models such as &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow's_hierarchy_of_needs"&gt;Maslow’s hierarchy of needs&lt;/a&gt; but my message in this talk is that we need to consider designing for behaviors using psychology and persuasion to create experiences. It is not just about the technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world with an increasing ubiquity of technology we are seeing more and more machines designed to persuade. We need to look to these types of approaches or we’re going to drown in a sea of noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International Conference on Persuasive Technology (Persuasive ‘09), &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1541999"&gt;A behavior model for persuasive design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persuasive Technology, Lecture Notes in Computer Science Volume 5033, 2008, &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-540-68504-3_3"&gt;Mass Interpersonal Persuasion: An Early View of a New Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psychological Review, 50, 370-396, 1943, &lt;a href="http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Maslow/motivation.htm"&gt;A theory of human motivation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 19: Discovery and orchestration - the missing glue for seamless immediate interaction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="19" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the next killer technology for mobile and for ubiquitous technology will be in discovery and orchestration. We need a solution to provide the platform to build seamless immediate interactions within a host of clamoring voices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 20: Don’t Panic&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" data-slide="20" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To quote Douglas Adams “Don’t Panic”, there are approaches to addressing ubiquitous and mobile technology. We simply need to move beyond the traditional toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/Design"/><category term="defuse"/><category term="design"/><category term="ux"/><category term="ixda"/><category term="mobile"/><category term="internet of things"/><category term="persuasive design"/><category term="ubiquitous technology"/></entry><entry><title>Omnigraffle, Climacons and Font Awesome</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/omnigrafflestencilforfonts.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2013-10-30:/omnigrafflestencilforfonts.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently been doing a few sketches using &lt;a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/products/omnigraffle/"&gt;Omnigraffle&lt;/a&gt; and realised that I had to create my first stencils to support the graphical prototyping I&amp;#8217;d been working on. The first font is the excellent &lt;a href="http://fortawesome.github.io/Font-Awesome/"&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/a&gt; and it already had a great stencil from &lt;a href="http://www.patcheung.com/2013/06/font-awesome-omnigraffle-stencil-project/"&gt;Pat Cheung&lt;/a&gt; that I merely …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently been doing a few sketches using &lt;a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/products/omnigraffle/"&gt;Omnigraffle&lt;/a&gt; and realised that I had to create my first stencils to support the graphical prototyping I’d been working on. The first font is the excellent &lt;a href="http://fortawesome.github.io/Font-Awesome/"&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/a&gt; and it already had a great stencil from &lt;a href="http://www.patcheung.com/2013/06/font-awesome-omnigraffle-stencil-project/"&gt;Pat Cheung&lt;/a&gt; that I merely needed to update from his &lt;a href="http://www.patcheung.com/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil"&gt;version&lt;/a&gt; to include the latest release of the font. The second font was a really nice climate icon font, &lt;a href="http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/"&gt;Climacons&lt;/a&gt; that did not have any stencil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really took some inspiration from Pat’s work and have sent a pull request back to his Github so hopefully the stencil will be updated. I really think that Dave Gandy and all the Font Awesome contributors have really created something so useful for wire framing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Font Awesome Stencil&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, down load the system font file from the &lt;a href="http://fortawesome.github.io"&gt;project’s website&lt;/a&gt; and then install this font on your computer. You can then download the stencil from my (Github project)[https://github.com/braz/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil], double click the stencil file to install it. The links for these are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Font Awesome: &lt;a href="http://fontawesome.io"&gt;http://fontawesome.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Font Awesome 4.0.1 OmniGraffle Stencil github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil"&gt;https://github.com/braz/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Climacons Stencil&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, down load the system font file from the &lt;a href="http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/"&gt;project’s website&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href="https://github.com/AdamWhitcroft/Climacons"&gt;Github repository&lt;/a&gt; and then install this font on your computer. You can then download the stencil from my (Github project)[https://github.com/braz/climacons-omnigraffle-stencil]], double click the stencil file to install it. The links for these are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climacons font: &lt;a href="http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/"&gt;http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climacons github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/AdamWhitcroft/Climacons"&gt;https://github.com/AdamWhitcroft/Climacons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climacons Omnigraffle Stencil github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/climacons-omnigraffle-stencil"&gt;https://github.com/braz/climacons-omnigraffle-stencil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you find these of use and feel free to submit pull requests as I intend to try and keep these updated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/Design"/><category term="omnigraffle"/><category term="fonts"/><category term="stencils"/><category term="design"/></entry><entry><title>Introduction to Machine Learning with R</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/introtomlwithr.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-10-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-10-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2013-10-08:/introtomlwithr.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting to the &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on machine learning. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-treesandforests/"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was aimed at introducing machine learning to the group as I hope to follow this talk up with more intermediate&amp;nbsp;topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/DublinR - Machine Learning 101 - Introduction with Examples.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting to the &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on machine learning. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-treesandforests/"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was aimed at introducing machine learning to the group as I hope to follow this talk up with more intermediate topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/pdfs/DublinR - Machine Learning 101 - Introduction with Examples.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; version of this talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The techniques covered included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model assessment and selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a confusion matrix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ROC&lt;/span&gt; plot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approaches to handling prediction errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addressing feature selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kaggle and data science competitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A review of various &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; techniques:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Associate rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision trees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Random forests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;k Nearest Neighbors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neural networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support vector machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naive bayesian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenRefine and Rattle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Useful command line tools for a data scientist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classification of objects into groups is a everyday task for humans and this talk helps highlight how to develop models to allow machines to do these tasks. The talk provide a quick understanding of machine learning algorithms showing how they worked, so that people would know when and how to best apply them. Machine learning and particularly feature generation for those models is seen as a “black art” due to the fact that domain expertise is required. The talk was aimed at showing people how R can be used in the process of selecting, assessing and creating models. It gave four datasets to show examples of exploratory data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talk slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;script async="" class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="2cd19ca020bf0131063f72abddee51e1" data-ratio="1.41436464088398" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Blog/R"/><category term="r"/><category term="presentations"/><category term="machine learning"/><category term="rstats"/></entry></feed>