<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Insights - Blog/SRE</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/feeds/blogsre.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://eoinbrazil.com/</id><updated>2015-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Recapping SRECon EU 2015</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recappart2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-06-13:/sreconeu2015recappart2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second part of my notes and thoughts on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recap.html"&gt;first part&lt;/a&gt; covers focuses on the workshops and some of the talks I&amp;nbsp;attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Opening Keynote - PostOps: Recovery from&amp;nbsp;Operations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tone of the conference was set by Todd Underwood who is the Director …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second part of my notes and thoughts on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recap.html"&gt;first part&lt;/a&gt; covers focuses on the workshops and some of the talks I&amp;nbsp;attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Opening Keynote - PostOps: Recovery from&amp;nbsp;Operations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tone of the conference was set by Todd Underwood who is the Director of Google&amp;#8217;s Site Reliability Engineering team. He neatly laid out and introduced &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SRE&lt;/span&gt; as the systems and software engineers who solve production problems with software. The concepts are inspired some what from Adrian Cockcroft&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;NoOps&amp;#8221; where there is no operations organisation and it is software developers supported by automation who are working directly with production. This isn&amp;#8217;t to say you shouldn&amp;#8217;t take the best of operations culture and apply it to your production engineering team. Site reliability engineering needs to be taken as a first-class responsibility / citizen. The talk was a good summary of the various concerns and history as to why the computing sector needs to move beyond the definitions of &amp;#8220;Administration&amp;#8221; and of&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;Operations&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Prometheus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://prometheus.io/"&gt;Prometheus&lt;/a&gt; is a new monitoring system built by a number of engineers from SoundCloud and several former Google SREs. This &lt;a href="https://developers.soundcloud.com/blog/prometheus-monitoring-at-soundcloud"&gt;Soundcloud Developers post introduces&lt;/a&gt; the system and how it has been designed to overcome issues they found with StatsD and Graphite. The four key features they highlighted during the talk where:
1. A multi-dimensional data model which allows pretty manuipulation of dimensions of the data
2. Simplicity to install and operate
3. Scalable data collection and decentralized architecture (time series collection via a pull model over &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;)
4. A query&amp;nbsp;language&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has a number of very useful features building on the work for systems like &lt;a href="http://opentsdb.net/"&gt;OpenTSDB&lt;/a&gt; and it has pretty much the same data model and syntax as OpenTSDB. This is where time series is identified by a metric name and a set of key-value pairs. These can be queried by its expression browser and the data can be visualised on dashboard using their PromDash tool. It hooks into to the likes of PagerDuty and supports a Nagios plugin allowing Prometheus to &amp;#8216;bridge&amp;#8217; to existing Nagios&amp;nbsp;deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big change is that Prometheus requires you to instrument your own code directly. The rationale for this is that is will provide higher quality service based monitoring.n instrumentation is usually worth the price. There are a range of client libraries for most programming languages. These client libraries allow metrics to be exposed via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; using either the protocol buffers format or as a simpler text-based&amp;nbsp;format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Prometheus servers scrape metrics from the instrumented applications directly or using a gateway. These samples then stored locally with rules executed over this data to generate new timeseries or to generate alerts. These streams of timestamped values all belong to the same metric with the same labeled dimesions. Timestamps are at a resolution of a millisecond resolution and the values are saved as 64-bit&amp;nbsp;floats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a range of blogs about it but I&amp;#8217;d highly recommend my fellow programme committee member Brian Brazil&amp;#8217;s series monitoring on the &lt;a href="http://www.boxever.com/tag/monitoring"&gt;Boxever blog&lt;/a&gt;. He was key team player in helping to organising the conference and is a committer to&amp;nbsp;Prometheus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Signatures, Patterns, and Trends: Timeseries Data Mining at&amp;nbsp;Etsy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can well imagine one of the maxims at Etsy being, if it moves, measure it and even if it doesn&amp;#8217;t, measure it. They record a ton of metrics and now have over a million metrics. This means they&amp;#8217;re literally drowning in data and traditional approaches means that both alerting and graphicing are not cutting it. Graphs don&amp;#8217;t scale well to a million distinct metrics and alert thresholds become very prone to triggering due to false&amp;nbsp;positives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to manage this magnitude of metrics they have developed the &lt;a href="https://codeascraft.com/2013/06/11/introducing-kale/"&gt;Kale stack&lt;/a&gt;. It consists of &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/skyline"&gt;Skyline&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/oculus"&gt;Oculus&lt;/a&gt;, the first help detects anomalous metrics and the latter is used to correlate patterns between metrics. This stack helps them detect any issues and make better hyptotheses around their&amp;nbsp;problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I definitely like the &amp;#8216;hack&amp;#8217; with the shape description alphabet for a timeseries similarity. The Etsy stack is focused on their problem of lots of metrics and how to monitor the million+ interdependent time-series. It stores these time series in Redis and uses ElasticSearch for the search component. The next iteration of the stack, &amp;#8216;Thyme&amp;#8217;, was the latter end of the talk and looks pretty&amp;nbsp;cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Upgrade Your Database without Losing Your Data, Your Perf, or Your&amp;nbsp;Mind&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charity Majors as ever gave an excellent talk that helped open the minds of many to the dangers of database upgrades. There is a shorter and earlier version of &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/charity/upgrading-databases-without-losing-your-data-your-perf-or-your-mind"&gt;this online&lt;/a&gt;. I have to say go &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/majors"&gt;watch the video&lt;/a&gt; as it is one of the best talks but I&amp;#8217;m a bit biased towards this topic these&amp;nbsp;days!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It discusses the apprioriate levels of paranoia you should have, the need to balance effort against risk, and how to capture and replay production traffic to feed this the database. She talked a little bit about their &lt;a href="https://github.com/ParsePlatform/flashback"&gt;flashback tool for replaying MongoDB workloads&lt;/a&gt;. There is a more detailed blog on the Parse site covering &lt;a href="http://blog.parse.com/learn/engineering/mongodb-rocksdb-benchmark-setup-compression/"&gt;how to setup this tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Going Off the Rails: Infrastructure Outage&amp;nbsp;Planning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a nice talk reviewing some of the aspects of a major incident in the London Underground with hardware upgrades, hardware failure and insufficent planning all contributing. It particularly highlighted how the failure to implement one element of the plan around managing the loading/offloading of trains meant chaos and massive queues for passengers. There was a nice section on lesson learnt and plans to prevent future&amp;nbsp;incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk summarised this &lt;a href="https://www.networkrail.co.uk/review-into-disruption-affecting-kings-cross-and-paddington-services-27-December-2014.pdf"&gt;report from Network Rail on the incident&lt;/a&gt; and focused on what learnings SREs could take from&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Bad Machinery— Managing Interrupts Under&amp;nbsp;Load&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the Google Storage SREs gave a very interesting talk on the personal side of how we (as individuals) manage interruptions in complex and busy production situations. In the case of SREs who both write code and work oncall it is important to really value keeping the engineering in the flow doing one thing well. It echos an earlier Velocity 2014 talk from Etsy who spoke about &amp;#8220;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/watch?v=FLqucVb_et0"&gt;Mean Time to Sleep: Quantifying the On-Call Experience&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; which has &lt;a href="https://codeascraft.com/2014/06/19/opsweekly-measuring-on-call-experience-with-alert-classification/"&gt;a blog post&lt;/a&gt; and their &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/opsweekly"&gt;opsweekly tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These talks are very valuable as understanding and measuring the interrupts can help in crafting better contextualised alerts or in not alerting the engineer unless it is necessary. As more companies deployer larger systems and services these practices will become more wide spread but in the meanwhile it&amp;#8217;s great to see how others are managing this&amp;nbsp;issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Aside regarding hiring and managing&amp;nbsp;SREs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest ;login Usenix magazine (June 2015, Vol. 40, No. 3) has two great articles including one from Todd Underwood (opening keynote speaker). These are well worth a read to help understand the role and how to hire the calibre of people needed for this type of&amp;nbsp;role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/publications/login/june15/hiring-site-reliability-engineers"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Hiring Site Reliability Engineers&amp;#8221; by Chris Jones, Todd Underwood, and Shyjala&amp;nbsp;Nukala&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/publications/login/june15/hixson"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;The Systems Engineering Side of Site Reliability Engineering&amp;#8221; by David Hixson and Betsy&amp;nbsp;Beyer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog/SRE"></category><category term="sre"></category><category term="presentations"></category><category term="usenix"></category><category term="review"></category></entry><entry><title>Recapping SRECon EU 2015</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recap.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-06-07:/sreconeu2015recap.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of helping to organise as well as attending &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. I have pulled together a few of my notes and links of interest to recap what was an excellent conference. It was focused on operations engineering and on site reliability topics with speakers from many …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of helping to organise as well as attending &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. I have pulled together a few of my notes and links of interest to recap what was an excellent conference. It was focused on operations engineering and on site reliability topics with speakers from many of the big names (e.g. Google, Facebook, Yelp, Spotify amongst&amp;nbsp;others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal goals outside of my programme committee role for the conference where to find out what counterparts where doing in similar or larger organisations. My current role with MongoDB involves a lot of customer facing work and troubleshooting so I was very interested in the Postmortem and Large Scale Abstract Design workshops. I&amp;#8217;ve presented a lot of work to the Dublin R Usergroup on machine learning so I took the opportunity to attend a similar session from Splunk. I dipped in and out of the other sessions at the conference. In the reminder of this blog post, I&amp;#8217;ll firstly cover my notes from the three workshops then move to my notes from the various talks and finally add some useful tools / pointers from other&amp;nbsp;attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, the last topic and most scary talk was on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; data protection, specifically the view / thinking of the European Court of Justice (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECJ&lt;/span&gt;) and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; Safe Harbour agreements. It was given by Simon McGarr, a well known Irish socilitor who&amp;#8217;s been a great advocate of Digital Rights in Ireland. It painted a scary picture that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; may end with two distinct Internets before 2015 is finished once the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECJ&lt;/span&gt; makes a ruling (expected in Oct/Nov). I&amp;#8217;m not a legal expert so instead I&amp;#8217;ll refer you to a &lt;a href="http://eulawanalysis.blogspot.ie/2015/03/does-facebook-and-usa-violate-eu-data.html"&gt;recent summary&lt;/a&gt; by Simon&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Workshops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Postmortems&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I can safely say this session changed my thinking around Postmortems. I cannot recommend the work of Etsy and John Allspaw highly enough in this regard. He was fantastic and brought us on a journey of understanding helping us to evolve a more nuanced and mature sense of investigation as well providing links to a larger toolkit to facilitate such sessions. I think these two bullet points encapsulate John&amp;#8217;s teaching
 * &amp;#8220;Key goal of postmortems is to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEARN&lt;/span&gt; rather than bring list of TODOs away&amp;#8221;
 * &amp;#8220;Goal of workshop on Postmortems is to help you ask better questions not give a magic&amp;nbsp;process&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to facilitate their Postmortem process Etsy have developed their own tool &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/morgue/blob/master/README.md"&gt;Morgue&lt;/a&gt; that allows them to tag, annotation and extract/link to specific issues in their Jira ticketing system. There&amp;#8217;s a great talk by &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/devopsdays/morgue-helping-better-understand-events-by-building-a-post-mortem-tool-bethany-macri"&gt;Bethany Macri on the Morgue tool&lt;/a&gt; that explains it in more&amp;nbsp;depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reference for improving communications that John mentioned in his talk is the book &amp;#8220;Crucial Conversations&amp;#8221; and having recently bought a copy, I&amp;#8217;d also concur. I also got a pointer to another excellent post from Lara Hogan (also at Etsy) on &lt;a href="http://larahogan.me/blog/giving-presentation-feedback/"&gt;giving presentation feedback&lt;/a&gt;. Etsy really impressed me at SRECon and looking forward to more of their talks in the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work and thinking are influenced on the five steps (see below) based on Dekker&amp;#8217;s methodology. As such it very useful to read &lt;a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.411.4985&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf"&gt;&amp;#8220;Reconstructing human contributions to accidents- the new view on error and performance&amp;#8221; by Sidney &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W.A.&lt;/span&gt; Dekker&lt;/a&gt; to help understand this &amp;#8220;new thinking&amp;#8221; and the rationale behind&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five steps for a postmortem create a concept-depentant account from the context-specific event data:
1. outline the sequence of events in context-specific language
2. if necessary, break the sequence of events into episodes, if necessary (avoiding the global singular timeline)
3. determine how the world changed during each episode
4. identify what the focus of attention, the goals of people and what knowledge was active at that point in time
5. work up to a conceptual&amp;nbsp;description&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thinking and John&amp;#8217;s talk put forward the view that Reductionism is false that outcomes can be foreseen in complex systems, that time is reversible (you can&amp;#8217;t rewind the buffer to reconstruct), and likewise that complete knowledge is not attainable. It underlined that &amp;#8220;Why&amp;#8221; is a terrible question to ask and immediately translated to &amp;#8220;Who is responsible&amp;#8221;. In a postmortem, when you ask &amp;#8220;How&amp;#8221; it translate to &amp;#8220;What is responsbile&amp;#8221;. Once you ask &amp;#8220;Why&amp;#8221; you lose context and it means that at least half of the key context and details are lost. One of the worst methods for a postmortem is the &amp;#8220;Five Whys&amp;#8221; as not only does it lose context but it also further loses complexity as it linear sequential. It is much better to ask &amp;#8220;Why else&amp;#8221; and better again to ask &amp;#8220;How&amp;#8221;. A key point was that &amp;#8220;Why&amp;#8221; is often used as a technique to shutdown conversations. At this point, there was recommendation to read the book &amp;#8220;Crucial Conversations: Tools for Talking When Stakes Are High&amp;#8221; and it&amp;#8217;s definitely well worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so much useful stuff that John covered that a full blog series could be dedicated to it and my recommendation is that you view one of his many videos online if you&amp;#8217;re interested in learning&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Large Scale Abstract&amp;nbsp;Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great half day small team classroom event where a real-world large scale engineering problem was presented. Each team had to come up with as much of the following as time&amp;nbsp;allowed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A high-level design that scales&amp;nbsp;horizontally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial SLIs,&amp;nbsp;SLOs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimates for hardware required to run each&amp;nbsp;component&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If time permits, monitoring design and disaster testing&amp;nbsp;scenarios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a great exercise and I&amp;#8217;ll refain from saying too much more as we where asked to avoiding sharing the content as they will reuse it. However I can provide a few links to relevant&amp;nbsp;talks/slides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//people/jeff/stanford-295-talk.pdf"&gt;Software Engineering Advice from building Large Scale Systems by Jeff&amp;nbsp;Dean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.somethingsimilar.com/2013/01/14/notes-on-distributed-systems-for-young-bloods/"&gt;Notes on Distributed Systems for Young Bloods by Jeff&amp;nbsp;Hodges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/sites/default/files/conference/protected-files/srecon15europe_slides_nolan.pdf"&gt;Distributed Consensus Algorithms for Extreme Reliability by Laura&amp;nbsp;Nolan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Machine Learning on Machine&amp;nbsp;Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a great series on statistical and machine learning talks, I attended the latter but I&amp;#8217;ll include links to both for those who might want to refresh their statisticial skills:
1. &lt;a href="https://github.com/HeinrichHartmann/StatisticsTutorial"&gt;Statistics Tutorial for SREs by Heinrich Hartmann&lt;/a&gt;
2. &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1JsanuUB8_6ae2mWEWyCzxhgcoe68G8EzaDgrgKUOopA/edit#slide=id.g9bd6a2176_2_87"&gt;Machine Learning for Machine&amp;nbsp;Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The machine learning workshop was fast paced and required Splunk so if you&amp;#8217;re interested in following the slides you&amp;#8217;ll need to install it first. I learnt a few new tricks and enjoyed somebody else giving a talk on that topic (I&amp;#8217;ve done a similar talk but with R recently). It was particularly nice to see how to structure the introduction and Splunk is a very powerful tool that I&amp;#8217;ll definitely be learning/using&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was so many excellent talks that I can&amp;#8217;t list them all. The standards where high and presentations excellent. I&amp;#8217;ll include a few that cover the spectrum of topics&amp;nbsp;covered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Operational Software&amp;nbsp;Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theo Schlossnagle gave an excellent talk on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/schlossnagle"&gt;Operational Software Design&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/postwait/operational-software-design"&gt;full slides online&lt;/a&gt;. It covered many tools such as DTrace, &lt;a href="http://backtrace.io/"&gt;backtrace.io&lt;/a&gt;, and their own &lt;a href="https://github.com/circonus-labs/fq"&gt;fq&lt;/a&gt;. He wrote fq to replace RabbitMq due to a number of issues where it was unable to work for their monitoring needs. fq is a brokered message queue using a publish subscribe model. It has been designed for performance and large number of connected&amp;nbsp;clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia&amp;#8217;s Yandex (2nd search engine in Russia) talks about the types of load tests that they use and presented 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/yandex/yandex-tank"&gt;Yandex Tank&lt;/a&gt; their tool for this. The &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/sites/default/files/conference/protected-files/srecon15europe_slides_lavrenuke.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/lavrenuke"&gt;abstract&lt;/a&gt; covered the full depth of this&amp;nbsp;talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m tied as which was my best talk as to whether it was from Susan Coghlan on improving infrastructure performance using root cause analysis (+2.5x &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MTTF&lt;/span&gt;) or Avleen Vig on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/vig"&gt;remote working&lt;/a&gt;. Susan&amp;#8217;s talk was from the Argonne &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HPC&lt;/span&gt; National Lab and showed how over the last five years, their process has contributed to improved reliability (e.g. 5x improvement &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MTTI&lt;/span&gt;), utilization (10% increase), and changed the problem priortisation approach. I think Avleen Vig wins out on how Etsy manages the challenges faced by engineers, management, and organizations, and ways to address the issues to successfully build distributed&amp;nbsp;teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Useful&amp;nbsp;Tools/Links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of tools and links I got from the&amp;nbsp;talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Nagios&amp;nbsp;related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/nagios-herald"&gt;nagios-herald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://nagios.sourceforge.net/docs/3_0/largeinstalltweaks.html"&gt;Use the use_large_installation_tweaks configuration option in&amp;nbsp;Nagios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Zookeeper&amp;nbsp;related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/twitter/zktraffic"&gt;zktraffic, iptraf / top monitor for&amp;nbsp;ZooKeeper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Kafka&amp;nbsp;related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/edenhill/kafkacat"&gt;Kafkacat, a generic command line non-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JVM&lt;/span&gt; Apache Kafka producer and&amp;nbsp;consumer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Parsely/pykafka"&gt;PyKafka is a cluster-aware Kafka protocol client for python&lt;/a&gt;. It includes python implementations of Kafka producers and&amp;nbsp;consumers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/jamiealquiza/sangrenel"&gt;Apache Kafka load testing&amp;nbsp;weapon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/stealthly/gauntlet"&gt;Apache Kafka Test Framework for Producer and Consumers for Compatibility&amp;nbsp;Testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/stealthly/go_kafka_client"&gt;Go library for&amp;nbsp;Kafka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog/SRE"></category><category term="sre"></category><category term="presentations"></category><category term="usenix"></category><category term="review"></category></entry></feed>