<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Insights - Blog/HomeOffice</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/feeds/bloghomeoffice.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>http://eoinbrazil.com/</id><updated>2021-08-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Keeping your home internet up with an uninterruptible power supply</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/keeping-your-internet-up-with-ups.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-08-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2021-08-24:/keeping-your-internet-up-with-ups.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the age of working from home, work has mostly moved to the laptop for many. This means that the odd blip in terms of power normally on their machine. This isn&amp;#8217;t the case for your home network infrastructure, specifically your router and/or modem. A uninterruptible power supply …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the age of working from home, work has mostly moved to the laptop for many. This means that the odd blip in terms of power normally on their machine. This isn’t the case for your home network infrastructure, specifically your router and/or modem. A uninterruptible power supply (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt;) is essentially a big battery that is used to keep your hardware up when the power is out. Laptops essentially already have a big battery so in many cases a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; is not necessary where the power cuts last for minutes or a couple of hours at most. The recent uncertainty around the winter power supply in the Dublin region prompted me to look more into this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My backup power recipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly routers and modems are pretty low power, they run anywhere from a dozen watts to maybe twice that for the really fully featured models. This means that you can get a moderately powered &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; which will be able to offer power for an hour or more to these devices. I went with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt; and specifically with the &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/products/Back-UPS-Pro-BR-650VA-6-Outlets-AVR-LCD-Interface/P-BR650MI"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR650MI&lt;/span&gt; Back &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; Pro &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;650VA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dublin’s Winter 2022 Power Worries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real worry I had after hearing about the potential problems in Dublin’s power supply this winter (2022) was with brown outs and potentially surges. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19 has limited the maintenace on a number of generators in the national grid and they’re currently undergoing maintence there is an open question as to whether these will be fully functional for this winter, hence the power supply worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A power outage typically doesn’t impact your Internet Service Providers (ISPs) as they’ll normally have their equipment protected with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; and surge protectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Brown outs and surges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surges and brown outs are the two main reasons I went with slightly higher specification model from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt;. Understanding what a surge and a brown out will be helpful to why I chose that specification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brown out is the term for when there is a drop in voltage in the power system. This can be intentional (by the power company) or unintentional (or due to a failure). It’s the intentional brown out scenario with the limited power in Dublin that was the prime reason I got a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt;. I hope this does not happen but if it does, I wanted to be prepared. A brown out can be imposed by the power company in an effort to reduce load and prevent a full power outage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A surge is an abnormally high voltage lasting for a short period of time (millisecond typically), this most often is from lightning strikes. Many &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; offer features to protect against these shocks which can significantly damage sensitive electrical equipment like your router or modem. I’ve already got two &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/ie/en/products/APC-Essential-SurgeArrest-8-outlets-230V-UK/P-PM8-UK"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt; Surge Arrest Essential 8 socket&lt;/a&gt; protectors which I discuss in &lt;a href=""&gt;more depth in this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR650MI&lt;/span&gt; Back &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; Pro &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;650VA&lt;/span&gt; highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of features in this model that helped my choice. You can checkout the &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/products/Back-UPS-Pro-BR-650VA-6-Outlets-AVR-LCD-Interface/P-BR650MI"&gt;full specification on this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It offers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regulation of voltage, it steps up low voltage (brown out) and steps down high voltage (surge) before sending the power to your devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can start cold, so if the power goes completely there isn’t a lag in it providing power to the connected devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;390 Watts / 650 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VA&lt;/span&gt; reasonable sized battery to give around an hour or so of supply to the devices I intend to connect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Setup and installation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few photographs of the unboxing and setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; box and cables&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UPS boxed with cables" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ups-unboxed.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; connected to test battery and first power up&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UPS powered up but with nothing connected" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ups-setup-nothing-connected.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPS&lt;/span&gt; setup and connected to router and to modem&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UPS setup and running" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ups-setup-router-and-modem-connected.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>Krisp Audio Hijacked Loopbacked Zoom Calls</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/krisp-audiohijacked-loopbacked-zoom-calls.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2021-06-23:/krisp-audiohijacked-loopbacked-zoom-calls.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to write up a short post around the audio setup I am using for my day-to-day Zoom Calls. It might be helpful to others and it&amp;#8217;s really given my audio setup a&amp;nbsp;lift. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post covers the specific details that &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;my earlier post didn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/a&gt; as I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to write up a short post around the audio setup I am using for my day-to-day Zoom Calls. It might be helpful to others and it’s really given my audio setup a lift. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post covers the specific details that &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;my earlier post didn’t&lt;/a&gt; as I wanted to expand on my use of &lt;a href="https://krisp.ai/"&gt;Krisp&lt;/a&gt; and how everything is setup for &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt;. These details will allow anyone reading to replicate this configuration for their own conference calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Audio Hardware&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/microphones/podcaster"&gt;Rode Podcaster &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; Broadcast Microphone&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/psa1"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSA1&lt;/span&gt; Studio Boom Arm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/smr"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SMR&lt;/span&gt; Advanced Shock Mount&lt;/a&gt; for my audio hardware for calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Audio Software&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a huge fan of all things &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/"&gt;Rogue Amoeba&lt;/a&gt;, they simply make great software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; I use the advanced audio configuration to enable the original audio input and remove echo cancellation as well as to select a higher quality of audio. These settings are really important as otherwise all the later audio processing won’t really add much quality or value to your audio for other call participants. In most calls, you will still have to manually select use original audio and hopefully down the line that will be might also be a default setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Zoom setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/zoom_advanced_audio_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt;, I use firstly use &lt;a href="https://krisp.ai/"&gt;Krisp&lt;/a&gt; and I pipe my microphone to it as an input. It uses Deep Neural Networks to provide noise cancellation. It has ‘learnt’ many different noises and fairly seamlessly removes these from the audio input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; to further process the audio output from &lt;a href="https://krisp.ai/"&gt;Krisp&lt;/a&gt;. I use the following processing elements: Declick, Dehum, AUHighShelfFilter, AUPeakLimiter, and AUMultiBandCompressor. This is then sent to a ZoomOutputDevice from within the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AudioHijack setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/audio_hijack_zoom_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; processing chain, I’ve added a number of plugins from &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com"&gt;Waves Audio&lt;/a&gt; to further process the audio. Specifically these are: &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com/plugins/deesser"&gt;DeEsser (s)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com/plugins/ns1-noise-suppressor"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NS1&lt;/span&gt; (s)&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.waves.com/plugins/vocal-rider"&gt;Vocal Rider Live (s)&lt;/a&gt;. These further clear up any excessive sibilance, general noise, and dynamically control my vocal gain. After some use of this and particularly the vocal gain control, I added an additional processing element (Volume) within &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; to slightly boost the audio post all of the processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I use &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/loopback/"&gt;Loopback&lt;/a&gt; for wiring my Audio Hijack output to &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; and to also link &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/farrago/"&gt;Farrango&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt;. I find that &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/farrago/"&gt;Farrango&lt;/a&gt; is great as a sound board with a few extra sounds from &lt;a href="https://freesound.org/"&gt;FreeSound.org&lt;/a&gt; to add precanned sound effects to any call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Loopback setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/loopback_setup_zoom.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="software"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>Even more updates to my home office</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/even-more-home-office-updates.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2020-10-23:/even-more-home-office-updates.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post follows two earlier posts (&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-updates.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), which describe my furniture and equipment. This post focuses on three very optional pieces of equipment that I have added, an 8-way surge protector, a headphone amplifier, and an upgrade to my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; hub. I also figured I would mention an …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post follows two earlier posts (&lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-updates.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), which describe my furniture and equipment. This post focuses on three very optional pieces of equipment that I have added, an 8-way surge protector, a headphone amplifier, and an upgrade to my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; hub. I also figured I would mention an old workhorse that has been plugging away for years at home, my old reliable 4-bay &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Surge protector&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a reliable surge protecctor is something everyone should invest in once you have a decent amount of equipment. It is essentially one of those things you buy and hope you never have to use it, like insurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought two &lt;a href="https://www.apc.com/shop/ie/en/products/APC-Essential-SurgeArrest-8-outlets-230V-UK/P-PM8-UK"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;APC&lt;/span&gt; Surge Arrest Essential 8 socket&lt;/a&gt; protectors. This is a high-end model as it provides a good surge energy rating of 2754 Joules. The surge energy rating is how much energy the protector can absorb before it fails. A rating of 2000 and above is general on the high end of the ratings and aimed at computers with valuable data you want to protect or high value electronics. I use one unit for my home office and I bought a second unit to protect my router, my Unifi Dream Machine, and my home &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;. In the midst of day 2 of a 6 week lockdown, suddenly thinking about business continuity doesn’t seem like that bad a plan!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="APC Surge Arrest Essential 8 socket" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/apc_surge_protector_8way.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Headphone amplifier&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had not really gotten in the audiophile area before and this is my first headphone amplifier. Honestly, I was hesistant to get something but it turns out that there was a new entrant, &lt;a href="https://ifi-audio.com/products/zen-dac/"&gt;iFi Zen &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that was worth considering. I read &lt;a href="https://www.whathifi.com/reviews/ifi-zen-dac"&gt;this review from What Hifi?&lt;/a&gt; that really changed my mind. I took the advice in that review and also got a &lt;a href="https://ifi-audio.com/products/ipower/"&gt;iFi iPower X power supply&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this has greatly improved my listening experience. I haven’t yet upgraded to the likes of Spotify Premium (I’m thinking about it alright!) but even with the freemium version there is a clear improvement with my existing headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="iFi Zen DAC" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/ifi_zen_dac.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Thunderbolt 3 Mac Dock&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve added more and more accessories to my home office I was running out of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; ports on my old &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; hub which had 3 ports. I decided to upgrade the capacity and went for the &lt;a href="https://www.caldigit.com/ts3-plus/"&gt;Caldigit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TS3&lt;/span&gt; Plus&lt;/a&gt; which provides a 5 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt;-A ports and 2 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt;-C ports as well as a host of others including an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SD&lt;/span&gt; Card Reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also is powered and has sufficient power to both drive my accessories as well as charging my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a monitor but if I do decide to get one this unit will easily handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Home &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had a Home &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt; for storing various documents, videos, photos and songs. It is a &lt;a href="https://shop.westerndigital.com/products/network-attached-storage/wd-my-cloud-expert-series-ex4100"&gt;Western Digital &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EX4100&lt;/span&gt; 4-bay &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It works well and almost invisibly in the background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>Some updates to my home office</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-updates.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-09-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2020-09-10:/home-office-updates.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I wrote &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;a short piece on my home office setup&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to follow up on that as I&amp;#8217;ve added a few additional pieces of equipment, particularly I&amp;#8217;ve improved my web camera&amp;nbsp;significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Webcam, camera, and stand for&amp;nbsp;mounting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had previously used a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/hd-pro-webcam-c920"&gt;Logitech C920 …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I wrote &lt;a href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html"&gt;a short piece on my home office setup&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to follow up on that as I’ve added a few additional pieces of equipment, particularly I’ve improved my web camera significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Webcam, camera, and stand for mounting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had previously used a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/hd-pro-webcam-c920"&gt;Logitech C920 web cam&lt;/a&gt; instead of the Macbook standard webcam and the big change to my setup was adding a &lt;a href="https://fujifilm-x.com/global/products/cameras/x-t200/"&gt;Fujifilm X-T200&lt;/a&gt;. The camera is a mirrorless body and I managed to pick up a deal which included a &lt;a href="https://fujifilm-x.com/global/products/lenses/xc15-45mmf35-56-ois-pz/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUJINON&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XC15&lt;/span&gt;-45mm F3.5-5.6 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OIS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PZ&lt;/span&gt; lense&lt;/a&gt;. The deal and the fact that Fujifilm is one of several camera manufacturers who enabled their cameras to be used as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; web cams with a firmware update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to complete the setup I got a microphone stand, a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/ds1"&gt;Rode &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DS1&lt;/span&gt; Microphone Desk Stand&lt;/a&gt; with a &lt;a href="https://www.camvate.com/camvate-thread-adapter-microphone-stand-5-8quot-27-female-to-1-4quot-20-male-for-camera-monitor_p1361.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAMVATE&lt;/span&gt; 1/4” Male to 5/8” Female Microphone Stand Adapter&lt;/a&gt; to convert the microphone thread to a standard camera thread. The final part to mount the camera was a &lt;a href="https://joby.com/global/ballhead-3k-jb01513-bww/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JOBY&lt;/span&gt; BallHead 3K&lt;/a&gt;, I love Joby’s kit and whilst slightly more expense than other mounting options I’m happy to pay a premium for solid, reliable kit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Charging, Extra Batteries, Lens Hood and Lense filter&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The camera does charge via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; but it’s quite slow to charge (~6 hours). I found a great little charger that both quick and takes two batteries, &lt;a href="https://www.nitecorestore.com/NITECORE-FX1-Charger-for-Fujifilm-Camera-Battery-p/chg-nite-fx1.htm"&gt;Nitecore &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FX1&lt;/span&gt; Fujifilm W126/W126s 2 Hour Dual Slot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There isn’t a way to easily power the camera from mains power whilst it is in use so I also picked up to two additional batteries, a &lt;a href="https://www.hahnel.ie/irish-shop/productUrl/f126twin/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HL&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;F126S&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TWIN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PACK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I can easily juggle to my old webcam and swap the battery for meetings so I’m not too worried about this so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to protect the lense, I got a &lt;a href="https://hoyafilter.com/product/pro1d_protector/"&gt;Hoya Pro-1 Digital Protector&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.jjc.cc/index.php/Product/product_info/id/2172"&gt;a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JJC&lt;/span&gt; Lens Hood&lt;/a&gt;. I hope these aren’t needed to protect the lense but if they are I’d much prefer for both of these to take the damage rather than the lense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Chair mounted Green Screen&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally managed to find a green screen that would work with the limited space I had. The &lt;a href="https://www.gig-gear.com/products/cam-a-lot"&gt;Gig Gear Cam-A-Lot Video Conferencing Background Privacy Screen (Green/White)&lt;/a&gt; which simply folds out and sits on the back of your chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A pair of blue light glasses&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit using and abandoning a prior set of blue light glasses as they weren’t a good fit. Second time round, I’d seen a few folks talk about Ambr Eyewear for blue light glasses (here’s looking at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AlanMeaney"&gt;Alan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/patphelan"&gt;Pat&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jesskellynt"&gt;Jess Kelly&lt;/a&gt;) so I went and got a pair of &lt;a href="https://ambreyewear.com/collections/our-range/products/zenith"&gt;Zenith glasses from them&lt;/a&gt;. A week on and I have to admit they do appear to be helping and most importantly they fit well so I’m much more likely to be wearing them for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="hardware"/></entry><entry><title>My home office and it’s bill of materials</title><link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/home-office-bill-of-materials.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Eoin Brazil</name></author><id>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2020-08-10:/home-office-bill-of-materials.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My home office is literally a desk in the corner of a bedroom which is returned to use as a bedroom after I finish work. All the setup and gear I has to fit this&amp;nbsp;requirement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Furniture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fold away desk isn&amp;#8217;t a typical order but in Dublin there …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My home office is literally a desk in the corner of a bedroom which is returned to use as a bedroom after I finish work. All the setup and gear I has to fit this requirement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Furniture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fold away desk isn’t a typical order but in Dublin there were two companies, &lt;a href="https://ministryofmakers.ie/"&gt;Ministry of Makers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.flyingelephant.ie/"&gt;Flying Elephant&lt;/a&gt; who supply desks that fit the criteria. I went the Halfway desk from Ministry of Makers and even coated it a few times with Danish Oil for good measure. I couldn’t find a fold away chair that I liked nor could I justify buying an Aeron, in the end I went for a &lt;a href="https://www.koplus.eu/en/products/tonique"&gt;Koplus &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TONIQUE&lt;/span&gt; Ergonomic mesh chair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Laptop, mouse and webcam&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My computer is a MacBook and I use it with a &lt;a href="https://griffintechnology.com/products/elevator"&gt;Griffin Elavator stand&lt;/a&gt; as well as a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-roeu/product/wireless-trackball-m570"&gt;Logitech wireless m570 trackball mouse&lt;/a&gt;. I use an &lt;a href="https://www.editorskeys.com/products/vi-vim-keyboard-covers-for-macbook-imac"&gt;EditorsKey Vi cover&lt;/a&gt; on it which probably has saved it from disaster too often to count. I use a &lt;a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-us/product/hd-pro-webcam-c920"&gt;Logitech C920 web cam&lt;/a&gt; instead of the Macbook standard webcam, it’s definitely an improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Networking gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I upgraded my home network during May to a &lt;a href="https://eu.store.ui.com/products/unifi-dream-machine"&gt;Unifi Dream Machine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://eu.store.ui.com/collections/unifi/products/unifi-flexhd"&gt;FlexHD&lt;/a&gt; primarily inspired by &lt;a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/friends-dont-let-friends-use-dodgy-wifi-introducing-ubiquitis-dream-machine-and-flexhd/"&gt;this post from Troy Hunt&lt;/a&gt;. It has been brilliant and I can’t recommend it highly enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Audio gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use two different audio recording configurations, the normal day to day uses a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/microphones/podcaster"&gt;Rode Podcaster &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; Broadcast Microphone&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/psa1"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSA1&lt;/span&gt; Studio Boom Arm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.rode.com/accessories/smr"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SMR&lt;/span&gt; Advanced Shock Mount&lt;/a&gt; for my normal calls (typically Zoom). I use a second setup for recording voice overs which uses a &lt;a href="https://countryman.com/product/e6-earset/"&gt;Countryman E6 Omni &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XLR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (over ear mic) and a &lt;a href="https://www.senalsound.com/product/7950/Senal-XU_1648-XLR_to_USB-Interface"&gt;Senal &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XLR&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XU&lt;/span&gt;-1648&lt;/a&gt;. These are fed through some audio software I’ll cover separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a set of closed &lt;a href="https://www.audio-technica.com/en-us/ath-m40x"&gt;Audio-Technica &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ATH&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;M40X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for my headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lighting gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My lighting is from a &lt;a href="https://www.elgato.com/en/gaming/key-light-air"&gt;Elgato Key Light Air&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="https://lumecube.com/products/video-conference-lighting-kit-for-remote-workers"&gt;LumeCube Video Conference Lighting for Remote Working&lt;/a&gt;. I only recently got the Elgato and it’s replaced LumeCube as my main light. I plan on using the much smaller LubeCube as a secondary light or when traveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Additional gear for various tasks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a &lt;a href="https://www.hootoo.com/p/b07yb2znrn"&gt;HooToo &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; C Hub&lt;/a&gt; to manage all the peripherals. I have a few extras pieces that I use for teaching including a &lt;a href="https://shop.astropad.com/"&gt;Luna Display&lt;/a&gt; (allows me to use an iPad as a second screen and indeed input to my laptop), a pair of &lt;a href="https://joby.com/global/gorillapod-flexible-camera-tripods/"&gt;Joby Gorillapod tripods&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MEKO&lt;/span&gt; Upgraded Fine Tip Stylus Pen for an iPad. I also have a &lt;a href="https://joby.com/global/griptight-pro-2-mount-jb01525-bww/"&gt;Joby GripTight Pro 2&lt;/a&gt; which I use to hold my phone as an ad-hoc whiteboard with the &lt;a href="https://reincubate.com/camo/"&gt;Camo app&lt;/a&gt;. I have also been experimenting with &lt;a href="https://obsproject.com/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OBS&lt;/span&gt; Open Broadcast Software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have a pack of &lt;a href="https://agilestationery.co.uk/products/video-conference-cards"&gt;Video Conference Cards&lt;/a&gt; from Agile Stationery which are great fun to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Software&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href="https://matthewpalmer.net/vanilla/"&gt;Vanilla&lt;/a&gt; to manage the menu bar, &lt;a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/amphetamine/id937984704"&gt;Amphetamine&lt;/a&gt; to keep my laptop on, &lt;a href="https://www.keyboardmaestro.com/main/"&gt;Keyboard Maestro&lt;/a&gt; for various macros, &lt;a href="https://folivora.ai/"&gt;BetterTouchTool&lt;/a&gt; for a nice toolbar, and &lt;a href="https://manytricks.com/witch/"&gt;Witch&lt;/a&gt; for window screen switching. I use &lt;a href="https://www.yellowmug.com/snapndrag/"&gt;SnapNDrag Pro&lt;/a&gt; for screen or window captures. I use &lt;a href="https://www.telestream.net/screenflow/overview.htm"&gt;ScreenFlow&lt;/a&gt; for capturing the voice overs of lessons and indeed any video offline capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of my audio software, I went all in on &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/"&gt;Rogue Amoeba&lt;/a&gt; and love all of their software. I use &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/soundsource/"&gt;SoundSource&lt;/a&gt; for managing my sources, &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/audiohijack/"&gt;Audio Hijack&lt;/a&gt; for various tasks including some preprocessing on my mic input, &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/loopback/"&gt;Loopback&lt;/a&gt; for wiring my Audio Hijack output to my Zoom or desired application, and &lt;a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/farrago/"&gt;Farrango&lt;/a&gt; for adding the odd random sound effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;SoundSource Setup&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SoundSource setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/soundsource_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Audio Hijack Setup&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AudioHijack setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/audio_hijack_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Loopback Setup&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Loopback setup" src="http://eoinbrazil.com/extras/loopback_setup.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog/HomeOffice"/><category term="office"/><category term="equipment"/><category term="software"/><category term="hardware"/></entry></feed>