<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Insights</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://eoinbrazil.com/feeds/eoin-brazil.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>About</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/about-me.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m a technology guy with a background in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UX&lt;/span&gt;, computer science and technology commercialisation. I&amp;#8217;ve spent several years working bringing research to commercialisation and managing consultancy projects with companies in Ireland and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love science, technology, craft beer, whisky and&amp;nbsp;statistics.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Eoin Brazil</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-06-08:about-me.html</guid></item><item><title>Recapping SRECon EU 2015</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/sreconeu2015recap.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of helping to organise as well as attending &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program"&gt;SRECon Europe 2015&lt;/a&gt;. I have pulled together a few of my notes and links of interest to recap what was an excellent conference. It was focused on operations engineering and on site reliability topics with speakers from many of the big names (e.g. Google, Facebook, Yelp, Spotify amongst&amp;nbsp;others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal goals outside of my programme committee role for the conference where to find out what counterparts where doing in similar or larger organisations. My current role with MongoDB involves a lot of customer facing work and troubleshooting so I was very interested in the Postmortem and Large Scale Abstract Design workshops. I&amp;#8217;ve presented a lot of work to the Dublin R Usergroup on machine learning so I took the opportunity to attend a similar session from Splunk. I dipped in and out of the other sessions at the conference. In the reminder of this blog post, I&amp;#8217;ll firstly cover my notes from the three workshops then move to my notes from the various talks and finally add some useful tools / pointers from other&amp;nbsp;attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, the last topic and most scary talk was on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; data protection, specifically the view / thinking of the European Court of Justice (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECJ&lt;/span&gt;) and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; Safe Harbour agreements. It was given by Simon McGarr, a well known Irish socilitor who&amp;#8217;s been a great advocate of Digital Rights in Ireland. It painted a scary picture that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; may end with two distinct Internets before 2015 is finished once the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECJ&lt;/span&gt; makes a ruling (expected in Oct/Nov). I&amp;#8217;m not a legal expert so instead I&amp;#8217;ll refer you to a &lt;a href="http://eulawanalysis.blogspot.ie/2015/03/does-facebook-and-usa-violate-eu-data.html"&gt;recent summary&lt;/a&gt; by Simon&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Workshops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Postmortems&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I can safely say this session changed my thinking around Postmortems. I cannot recommend the work of Etsy and John Allspaw highly enough in this regard. He was fantastic and brought us on a journey of understanding helping us to evolve a more nuanced and mature sense of investigation as well providing links to a larger toolkit to facilitate such sessions. I think these two bullet points encapsulate John&amp;#8217;s teaching
 * &amp;#8220;Key goal of postmortems is to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEARN&lt;/span&gt; rather than bring list of TODOs away&amp;#8221;
 * &amp;#8220;Goal of workshop on Postmortems is to help you ask better questions not give a magic&amp;nbsp;process&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to facilitate their Postmortem process Etsy have developed their own tool &lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/morgue/blob/master/README.md"&gt;Morgue&lt;/a&gt; that allows them to tag, annotation and extract/link to specific issues in their Jira ticketing system. There&amp;#8217;s a great talk by &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/devopsdays/morgue-helping-better-understand-events-by-building-a-post-mortem-tool-bethany-macri"&gt;Bethany Macri on the Morgue tool&lt;/a&gt; that explains it in more&amp;nbsp;depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reference for improving communications that John mentioned in his talk is the book &amp;#8220;Crucial Conversations&amp;#8221; and having recently bought a copy, I&amp;#8217;d also concur. I also got a pointer to another excellent post from Lara Hogan (also at Etsy) on &lt;a href="http://larahogan.me/blog/giving-presentation-feedback/"&gt;giving presentation feedback&lt;/a&gt;. Etsy really impressed me at SRECon and looking forward to more of their talks in the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work and thinking are influenced on the five steps (see below) based on Dekker&amp;#8217;s methodology. As such it very useful to read &lt;a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.411.4985&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf"&gt;&amp;#8220;Reconstructing human contributions to accidents- the new view on error and performance&amp;#8221; by Sidney &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W.A.&lt;/span&gt; Dekker&lt;/a&gt; to help understand this &amp;#8220;new thinking&amp;#8221; and the rationale behind&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five steps for a postmortem create a concept-depentant account from the context-specific event data:
1. outline the sequence of events in context-specific language
2. if necessary, break the sequence of events into episodes, if necessary (avoiding the global singular timeline)
3. determine how the world changed during each episode
4. identify what the focus of attention, the goals of people and what knowledge was active at that point in time
5. work up to a conceptual&amp;nbsp;description&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thinking and John&amp;#8217;s talk put forward the view that Reductionism is false that outcomes can be foreseen in complex systems, that time is reversible (you can&amp;#8217;t rewind the buffer to reconstruct), and likewise that complete knowledge is not attainable. It underlined that &amp;#8220;Why&amp;#8221; is a terrible question to ask and immediately translated to &amp;#8220;Who is responsible&amp;#8221;. In a postmortem, when you ask &amp;#8220;How&amp;#8221; it translate to &amp;#8220;What is responsbile&amp;#8221;. Once you ask &amp;#8220;Why&amp;#8221; you lose context and it means that at least half of the key context and details are lost. One of the worst methods for a postmortem is the &amp;#8220;Five Whys&amp;#8221; as not only does it lose context but it also further loses complexity as it linear sequential. It is much better to ask &amp;#8220;Why else&amp;#8221; and better again to ask &amp;#8220;How&amp;#8221;. A key point was that &amp;#8220;Why&amp;#8221; is often used as a technique to shutdown conversations. At this point, there was recommendation to read the book &amp;#8220;Crucial Conversations: Tools for Talking When Stakes Are High&amp;#8221; and it&amp;#8217;s definitely well worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so much useful stuff that John covered that a full blog series could be dedicated to it and my recommendation is that you view one of his many videos online if you&amp;#8217;re interested in learning&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Large Scale Abstract&amp;nbsp;Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great half day small team classroom event where a real-world large scale engineering problem was presented. Each team had to come up with as much of the following as time&amp;nbsp;allowed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A high-level design that scales&amp;nbsp;horizontally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial SLIs,&amp;nbsp;SLOs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimates for hardware required to run each&amp;nbsp;component&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If time permits, monitoring design and disaster testing&amp;nbsp;scenarios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a great exercise and I&amp;#8217;ll refain from saying too much more as we where asked to avoiding sharing the content as they will reuse it. However I can provide a few links to relevant&amp;nbsp;talks/slides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//people/jeff/stanford-295-talk.pdf"&gt;Software Engineering Advice from building Large Scale Systems by Jeff&amp;nbsp;Dean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.somethingsimilar.com/2013/01/14/notes-on-distributed-systems-for-young-bloods/"&gt;Notes on Distributed Systems for Young Bloods by Jeff&amp;nbsp;Hodges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/sites/default/files/conference/protected-files/srecon15europe_slides_nolan.pdf"&gt;Distributed Consensus Algorithms for Extreme Reliability by Laura&amp;nbsp;Nolan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Machine Learning on Machine&amp;nbsp;Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a great series on statistical and machine learning talks, I attended the latter but I&amp;#8217;ll include links to both for those who might want to refresh their statisticial skills:
1. &lt;a href="https://github.com/HeinrichHartmann/StatisticsTutorial"&gt;Statistics Tutorial for SREs by Heinrich Hartmann&lt;/a&gt;
2. &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1JsanuUB8_6ae2mWEWyCzxhgcoe68G8EzaDgrgKUOopA/edit#slide=id.g9bd6a2176_2_87"&gt;Machine Learning for Machine&amp;nbsp;Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The machine learning workshop was fast paced and required Splunk so if you&amp;#8217;re interested in following the slides you&amp;#8217;ll need to install it first. I learnt a few new tricks and enjoyed somebody else giving a talk on that topic (I&amp;#8217;ve done a similar talk but with R recently). It was particularly nice to see how to structure the introduction and Splunk is a very powerful tool that I&amp;#8217;ll definitely be learning/using&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was so many excellent talks that I can&amp;#8217;t list them all. The standards where high and presentations excellent. I&amp;#8217;ll include a few that cover the spectrum of topics&amp;nbsp;covered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Operational Software&amp;nbsp;Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theo Schlossnagle gave an excellent talk on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/schlossnagle"&gt;Operational Software Design&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/postwait/operational-software-design"&gt;full slides online&lt;/a&gt;. It covered many tools such as DTrace, &lt;a href="http://backtrace.io/"&gt;backtrace.io&lt;/a&gt;, and their own &lt;a href="https://github.com/circonus-labs/fq"&gt;fq&lt;/a&gt;. He wrote fq to replace RabbitMq due to a number of issues where it was unable to work for their monitoring needs. fq is a brokered message queue using a publish subscribe model. It has been designed for performance and large number of connected&amp;nbsp;clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia&amp;#8217;s Yandex (2nd search engine in Russia) talks about the types of load tests that they use and presented 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/yandex/yandex-tank"&gt;Yandex Tank&lt;/a&gt; their tool for this. The &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/sites/default/files/conference/protected-files/srecon15europe_slides_lavrenuke.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/lavrenuke"&gt;abstract&lt;/a&gt; covered the full depth of this&amp;nbsp;talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m tied as which was my best talk as to whether it was from Susan Coghlan on improving infrastructure performance using root cause analysis (+2.5x &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MTTF&lt;/span&gt;) or Avleen Vig on &lt;a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon15europe/program/presentation/vig"&gt;remote working&lt;/a&gt;. Susan&amp;#8217;s talk was from the Argonne &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HPC&lt;/span&gt; National Lab and showed how over the last five years, their process has contributed to improved reliability (e.g. 5x improvement &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MTTI&lt;/span&gt;), utilization (10% increase), and changed the problem priortisation approach. I think Avleen Vig wins out on how Etsy manages the challenges faced by engineers, management, and organizations, and ways to address the issues to successfully build distributed&amp;nbsp;teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Useful&amp;nbsp;Tools/Links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of tools and links I got from the&amp;nbsp;talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Nagios&amp;nbsp;related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/etsy/nagios-herald"&gt;nagios-herald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://nagios.sourceforge.net/docs/3_0/largeinstalltweaks.html"&gt;Use the use_large_installation_tweaks configuration option in&amp;nbsp;Nagios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Zookeeper&amp;nbsp;related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/twitter/zktraffic"&gt;zktraffic, iptraf / top monitor for&amp;nbsp;ZooKeeper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Kafka&amp;nbsp;related&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/edenhill/kafkacat"&gt;Kafkacat, a generic command line non-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JVM&lt;/span&gt; Apache Kafka producer and&amp;nbsp;consumer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Parsely/pykafka"&gt;PyKafka is a cluster-aware Kafka protocol client for python&lt;/a&gt;. It includes python implementations of Kafka producers and&amp;nbsp;consumers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/jamiealquiza/sangrenel"&gt;Apache Kafka load testing&amp;nbsp;weapon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/stealthly/gauntlet"&gt;Apache Kafka Test Framework for Producer and Consumers for Compatibility&amp;nbsp;Testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/stealthly/go_kafka_client"&gt;Go library for&amp;nbsp;Kafka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Eoin Brazil</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-06-07:sreconeu2015recap.html</guid><category>sre</category><category>presentations</category><category>usenix</category><category>review</category></item><item><title>My Previous Research</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/my-research.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a hectic few months learning the ins and outs of MongoDB. I&amp;#8217;ve learnt a lot but a request has made me realise that I&amp;#8217;d forgotten to bring a few artefacts from my past along with me and that the Internet has forgotten them as well. Over the years the links to my various disserations and theses have fallen out of circulation due to replacement of webservers and general spring cleaning of former researcher group&amp;nbsp;members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m posting them back to this website with my apologies to those who in the research community couldn&amp;#8217;t access them, I honestly hadn&amp;#8217;t realise they were not still being hosted on the various&amp;nbsp;servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Investigation of multiple visualisation techniques and dynamic queries in conjunction with direct sonification to support the browsing of audio&amp;nbsp;resources&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Masters thesis investigated sound / music collection management from the view point of browsing coupled with multiple visualisations and filtering. The question asked sought to discover if supporting a different form of navigating these resources might enhance the serendipity of the experience. Looking at it today, it is still an open question as whilst Spotify and similar streaming music services provide a search inspired navigation approach, there is still no browse inspired approach that allows you to be lost in oceans of sound, and yet made those serendipitous&amp;nbsp;discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/15564389/msc_thesis.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Investigating Methods for the Selection and Evaluation of Everyday Sounds for Use As Auditory&amp;nbsp;Icons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PhD thesis investigated everyday sounds, specifically how people categorised these sounds and what meanings they associated with them. My work gathered a range of existing techniques from interaction design and from other domains to elict the multiple meanings that people assoicate with these sounds. The thesis provided a framework and guidance on how to map these meanings to usable categories. My eventual and still unreached goal was to design auditory interfaces using these sounds for public spaces where the sounds would have a communal meaning and a hidden/deeper personal meaning. The very essence of private communication with non-speech sounds in public environments where hidden messages could be passed to the listener due to the deeper understanding of how they would perceive the multiple layers of meaning inherent in the&amp;nbsp;sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/15564389/phd_thesis.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A Generic Approach for Data Management combining Financial Modeling with Road&amp;nbsp;Mapping&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PGDip dissertation in technology commercialisation investigated how road mapping could be combined with financial modeling and looked at this in the context of data management. It provided an approach for businesses that allowes for the development of a technology strategy with clearly outlined cost benefits to the business. Road maps, particular technology road maps are a common tool in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; product management mid to long term strategies, however these do not include any clear financial modeling that allows tangible estimates to be developed and matched to the road map. I had worked with a number of companies in the cloud and high-performance computing space during this period and felt the cloud hype (which unfortunately still exists today) needed better tools for senior &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; managers to both understand and justify their technology strategy&amp;nbsp;choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/15564389/pgdip_dissertation.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Eoin Brazil</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-03-22:my-research.html</guid></item><item><title>Machine Learning of Machines with R</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/machinemlwithr.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Following my introduction presentation to the &lt;a href="www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on machine learning, I again had the pleasure of being invited to talk on more machine learning. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-machine"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was more intermediate than my &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-treesandforests/"&gt;previous introductory talk&lt;/a&gt;. It used two datasets focusing on computing cluster job usage statistics (e.g. similar to data from a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HPC&lt;/span&gt; job scheduler) and machine level application and host usage statistics (e.g. similar to those from host monitoring software such as&amp;nbsp;Nagios).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The techniques covered&amp;nbsp;included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Background on large scale clusters (e.g. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HPC&lt;/span&gt;) and rationale for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; of machine/cluster operational&amp;nbsp;metrics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow for model&amp;nbsp;building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data&amp;nbsp;transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addressing feature&amp;nbsp;selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model assessment and&amp;nbsp;selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a confusion&amp;nbsp;matrix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ROC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;plot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approaches to handling prediction&amp;nbsp;errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boosting and&amp;nbsp;Bagging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data set 1 - Job scheduling&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data set 2 - Machine metrics&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary /&amp;nbsp;recap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Unused) A review of various &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; techniques:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision&amp;nbsp;trees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Random&amp;nbsp;forests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;k Nearest&amp;nbsp;Neighbors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support vector&amp;nbsp;machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk focused on the two datasets as well as highlightly how the business context was important to consider when developing the models. The talk looking at using machine learning to improvie the utilisation and scheduling of large scale clusters (significant hardware resources). It recapped some earlier material and focused a little more on feature selection and feature generation as well as applied domain expertise from the data set. It provides two datasets showing examples of how to use R to select, assess and create the&amp;nbsp;models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talk&amp;nbsp;slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="8afe1177b3be4840980b2f252a428b81" data-ratio="0.707182320441989" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Eoin Brazil</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2015-03-21:machinemlwithr.html</guid><category>r</category><category>presentations</category><category>machine learning</category><category>rstats</category></item><item><title>Handy Interaction Design - DEFUSE Dublin 2013</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/handyinteractiondesign.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate to have been asked to present at &lt;a href="http://www.ixd.ie/"&gt;IxDA Dublin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.defuse.ixd.ie/"&gt;Design for Use 2013 (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEFUSE&lt;/span&gt;) conference&lt;/a&gt; on interaction design. I&amp;#8217;ll briefly walk through my talk in this post as technical issues on the night left it a little disjointed. I&amp;#8217;ve included references used in the talk for those interested in diving a little deeper into the topics I&amp;nbsp;covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk was aimed at introducing persuasive design as one approach to dealing with the growth of mobile applications and beyond, particularly the increasing ubiquity of devices as illustrated by the Internet of&amp;nbsp;Things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 1 - 3: Our senses and humans as multimodal&amp;nbsp;creatures&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="2" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;&amp;#8216;&lt;/span&gt;Cortex&amp;#8217; man illustrates the amount of wiring in our brain that is dedicated to specific modalities. It highlights that we are multimodal creatures. In the past I&amp;#8217;ve worked on a range of alternative interfaces including buttons that you can hear but cannot see. In a world of increasing ubiquity of technology we need to re-imagine how we interact&amp;nbsp;technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IEEE&lt;/span&gt; Multimedia 2005, &lt;a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=1423932"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HCI&lt;/span&gt; Design and Interactive Sonification for Fingers and Ear&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 4 - 7: From desktop to motes and the growth of mobile apps to the Internet of&amp;nbsp;Things&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="4" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jumping to the thoughts of Scott Jenson and the realisation that we simply cannot create an interface or application for every piece of technology as we move from the desktop, to dedicated devices, to motes or invisible technology. The growth of the Internet of Things will drown in us in a cacophony of machine voice, all of which are seeking our most limited resource that of our&amp;nbsp;attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://mobile.smashingmagazine.com/2013/10/08/responsive-website-design-with-ress/"&gt;Responsive design with server side components&lt;/a&gt; and multi-device design all attempt a technological solution focusing on presentation or hardware issues. These are only part of the problem, interaction requires much more than just a technical&amp;nbsp;solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devices such as &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/glass/start/what-it-does/"&gt;Google&amp;#8217;s Glass&lt;/a&gt; or wearable ambient displays such as the &lt;a href="http://jorgeandesther.com/lume/"&gt;Lume&lt;/a&gt; show how we are only scratching the surface of what these devices can tell us about their usage, location and&amp;nbsp;context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog entry by Scott Jenson - August 1, 2012 &lt;a href="http://designmind.frogdesign.com/blog/of-bears-bats-and-bees-making-sense-of-the-internet-of-things.html"&gt;Of Bears, Bats, and Bees: Making Sense of the Internet of Things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 8 - 10: Emerging scenarios and contexts of use, device awareness of environment and responsive design/multi-device&amp;nbsp;design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="8" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies are showing us how people are using devices to tackle in a variety of ways that we are only beginning to design for and understand. Google&amp;#8217;s study on &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/think/research-studies/the-new-multi-screen-world-study.html"&gt;multi-device use for a variety of scenarios&lt;/a&gt; highlights how we need to re-consider interactions not just in terms of devices but also with regard to the relatedness of the activity and&amp;nbsp;behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developments on the technology side such as environmental awareness via Device APIs that allow devices to provide more information about their context of use can help and provide guidance on whether it is appropriate  to interact with the person. Testing and querying what a device can do will still be part of a solution but we also need to focus on behaviors, mental models and the abilities of people in designing new interactions for ubiquitous&amp;nbsp;technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google August 2012, &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/think/research-studies/the-new-multi-screen-world-study.html"&gt;Research Study - The New Multi-Screen World Study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Wright, February 12 - 2013, A List Apart, &lt;a href="http://alistapart.com/article/environmental-design-with-the-device-api"&gt;&amp;#8220;Environmental Design with the Device &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 11: A cavet, the difficulties of understanding and eliciting views of how people perceive the&amp;nbsp;world&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="11" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding and eliciting the views and contexts of how people perceive the world is &lt;bold&gt;difficult&lt;/bold&gt; and in this talk I only touch on a few approaches but there are many more that can&amp;nbsp;help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 12: - Moving beyond the traditional interface&amp;nbsp;paradigms&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="12" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to move beyond the command line and graphical user interface paradigms and really start to explore new paradigms such as the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_user_interface"&gt;natural user interfaces&lt;/a&gt; with the likes of &lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/surface/en-ie"&gt;Microsoft&amp;#8217;s Surface&lt;/a&gt; and other tangible&amp;nbsp;interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slides 13 - 18: Using models and approaches such as persuasive design to deal with attention and the clamouring noise from machines, services and applications competiting for&amp;nbsp;attention&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="13" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In tandem, we need to better model people&amp;#8217;s behaviors using the likes of &lt;a href="www.behaviormodel.org"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BJ&lt;/span&gt; Fogg&amp;#8217;s model&lt;/a&gt; which captures motivation, ability, and triggers. It looks at not just a single interaction but right up to changing or habituating&amp;nbsp;behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this type of approach work ? Mike Krieger is a former student of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BJ&lt;/span&gt; Fogg and co-founded Instagram. He uses &lt;a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/anthonykosner/2012/12/01/instagram-will-monetize-for-facebook-by-testing-solutions-one-week-at-a-time/"&gt;these approaches&lt;/a&gt; to decide what the new features will be included in&amp;nbsp;Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fogg has another paper on &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-540-68504-3_3"&gt;&amp;#8216;Mass Interpersonal Persuasion: An Early View of a New Phenomenon&amp;#8217;&lt;/a&gt; which looks at Facebook and the psychology of persuasion. It isn&amp;#8217;t exactly about creating a viral adoption model but it is a way of understanding how to reach and influence millions of people using this type of&amp;nbsp;technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other models such as &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow's_hierarchy_of_needs"&gt;Maslow&amp;#8217;s hierarchy of needs&lt;/a&gt; but my message in this talk is that we need to consider designing for behaviors using psychology and persuasion to create experiences. It is not just about the&amp;nbsp;technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world with an increasing ubiquity of technology we are seeing more and more machines designed to persuade. We need to look to these types of approaches or we&amp;#8217;re going to drown in a sea of&amp;nbsp;noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International Conference on Persuasive Technology (Persuasive &amp;#8216;09), &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1541999"&gt;A behavior model for persuasive design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persuasive Technology, Lecture Notes in Computer Science Volume 5033, 2008, &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-540-68504-3_3"&gt;Mass Interpersonal Persuasion: An Early View of a New Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psychological Review, 50, 370-396, 1943, &lt;a href="http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Maslow/motivation.htm"&gt;A theory of human motivation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 19: Discovery and orchestration - the missing glue for seamless immediate&amp;nbsp;interaction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="19" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the next killer technology for mobile and for ubiquitous technology will be in discovery and orchestration. We need a solution to provide the platform to build seamless immediate interactions within a host of clamoring&amp;nbsp;voices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Slide 20: Don&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;Panic&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="20" data-id="6b3c33302cf80131ff12122461a0ee5c" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To quote Douglas Adams &amp;#8220;Don&amp;#8217;t Panic&amp;#8221;, there are approaches to addressing ubiquitous and mobile technology. We simply need to move beyond the traditional&amp;nbsp;toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Eoin Brazil</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2013-11-11:handyinteractiondesign.html</guid><category>defuse</category><category>design</category><category>ux</category><category>ixda</category><category>mobile</category><category>internet of things</category><category>persuasive design</category><category>ubiquitous technology</category></item><item><title>Omnigraffle, Climacons and Font Awesome</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/omnigrafflestencilforfonts.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I recently been doing a few sketches using &lt;a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/products/omnigraffle/"&gt;Omnigraffle&lt;/a&gt; and realised that I had to create my first stencils to support the graphical prototyping I&amp;#8217;d been working on. The first font is the excellent &lt;a href="http://fortawesome.github.io/Font-Awesome/"&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/a&gt; and it already had a great stencil from &lt;a href="http://www.patcheung.com/2013/06/font-awesome-omnigraffle-stencil-project/"&gt;Pat Cheung&lt;/a&gt; that I merely needed to update from his &lt;a href="patcheung/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil"&gt;version&lt;/a&gt; to include the latest release of the font. The second font was a really nice climate icon font, &lt;a href="http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/"&gt;Climacons&lt;/a&gt; that did not have any&amp;nbsp;stencil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really took some inspiration from Pat&amp;#8217;s work and have sent a pull request back to his Github so hopefully the stencil will be updated. I really think that Dave Gandy and all the Font Awesome contributors have really created something so useful for wire&amp;nbsp;framing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Font Awesome&amp;nbsp;Stencil&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, down load the system font file from the &lt;a href="http://fortawesome.github.io"&gt;project&amp;#8217;s website&lt;/a&gt; and then install this font on your computer. You can then download the stencil from my (Github project)[https://github.com/braz/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil], double click the stencil file to install it. The links for these&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Font Awesome: &lt;a href="http://fontawesome.io"&gt;http://fontawesome.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Font Awesome 4.0.1 OmniGraffle Stencil github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil"&gt;https://github.com/braz/Font-Awesome-OmniGraffle-Stencil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Climacons&amp;nbsp;Stencil&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, down load the system font file from the &lt;a href="http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/"&gt;project&amp;#8217;s website&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href="https://github.com/AdamWhitcroft/Climacons"&gt;Github repository&lt;/a&gt; and then install this font on your computer. You can then download the stencil from my (Github project)[https://github.com/braz/climacons-omnigraffle-stencil]], double click the stencil file to install it. The links for these&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climacons font: &lt;a href="http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/"&gt;http://adamwhitcroft.com/climacons/font/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climacons github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/AdamWhitcroft/Climacons"&gt;https://github.com/AdamWhitcroft/Climacons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climacons Omnigraffle Stencil github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/climacons-omnigraffle-stencil"&gt;https://github.com/braz/climacons-omnigraffle-stencil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you find these of use and feel free to submit pull requests as I intend to try and keep these&amp;nbsp;updated.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Eoin Brazil</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2013-10-30:omnigrafflestencilforfonts.html</guid><category>omnigraffle</category><category>fonts</category><category>stencils</category><category>design</category></item><item><title>Introduction to Machine Learning with R</title><link>http://eoinbrazil.com/introtomlwithr.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting to the &lt;a href="www.meetup.com/DublinR/"&gt;Dublin R User Group&lt;/a&gt; on machine learning. My talk source and examples are in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/braz/DublinR-ML-treesandforests/"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was aimed at introducing machine learning to the group as I hope to follow this talk up with more intermediate&amp;nbsp;topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The techniques covered&amp;nbsp;included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data&amp;nbsp;transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model&amp;nbsp;building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model assessment and&amp;nbsp;selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a confusion&amp;nbsp;matrix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreting a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ROC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;plot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approaches to handling prediction&amp;nbsp;errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addressing feature&amp;nbsp;selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kaggle and data science&amp;nbsp;competitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A review of various &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; techniques:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Associate&amp;nbsp;rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision&amp;nbsp;trees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Random&amp;nbsp;forests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;k Nearest&amp;nbsp;Neighbors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neural&amp;nbsp;networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support vector&amp;nbsp;machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naive&amp;nbsp;bayesian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenRefine and&amp;nbsp;Rattle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Useful command line tools for a data&amp;nbsp;scientist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classification of objects into groups is a everyday task for humans and this talk helps highlight how to develop models to allow machines to do these tasks. The talk provide a quick understanding of machine learning algorithms showing how they worked, so that people would know when and how to best apply them. Machine learning and particularly feature generation for those models is seen as a &amp;#8220;black art&amp;#8221; due to the fact that domain expertise is required. The talk was aimed at showing people how R can be used in the process of selecting, assessing and creating models. It gave four datasets to show examples of exploratory data&amp;nbsp;analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talk&amp;nbsp;slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="2cd19ca020bf0131063f72abddee51e1" data-ratio="1.41436464088398" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Eoin Brazil</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:eoinbrazil.com,2013-10-08:introtomlwithr.html</guid><category>r</category><category>presentations</category><category>machine learning</category><category>rstats</category></item></channel></rss>